<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons Artillery briefly containing the noble practise of that wothie [sic] societie: with the moderne and ancient martiall exercises, natures of armes, vertue of magistrates, antiquitie, glorie and chronography of this honourable cittie. By R.N. Oxon.</title>
            <author>Niccols, Richard, 1584-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14996</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848441</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177744</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240894832</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18522</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S113204</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99848441e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177744)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1179:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons Artillery briefly containing the noble practise of that wothie [sic] societie: with the moderne and ancient martiall exercises, natures of armes, vertue of magistrates, antiquitie, glorie and chronography of this honourable cittie. By R.N. Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Niccols, Richard, 1584-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede, and Bernard Allsopp, for William Welby, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Richard Niccols.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>In the title, the comma after "Artillery" is printed above the line.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Londons Artillerie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army. --  Royal Artillery Company of London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:1"/>
            <p>LONDONS ARTILLERY, BRIEFLY CONTAINING The noble practise of that wothie Societie: WITH THE MODERNE AND AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient martiall exercises, natures of armes, vertue of Magistrates, Antiquitie, Glorie and Chronography of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Cittie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praemia virtutis nostrae, non stirpis honores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R.N. Oxon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Creede,</hi> and <hi>Bernard Allsopp,</hi> for <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Swan. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR <hi>IOHN IOLLES,</hi> KNIGHT, LORD Maior, and to the right VVorshipfull the Aldermen and Senate of the <hi>famous cittie of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S no riches doe better enrich the soule of man, then learning, and no learning doth better instruct the life of man, then Historie; so (right Honorable) no Historie can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beseeme your knowledge, then that of this noble Cittie; and since examples pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile more then precepts as patternes to follow, I haue broken some sleepe to awake from sleepe the worthie deedes of many your Honourable prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, who before you haue swayd the sword of Iustice in Londons Tribunall, which with her His<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of auncient and moderne times, Chronogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall description, polliticall gouernment, milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie exercises and natures of armes all taking begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the worthie practise of your now hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Infantrie, I haue published as the map of my natiue Lōdons glory, before neuer delineated in the like form or method: the cause why I haue conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated
<pb facs="tcp:177744:3"/> it vnto your Honor is my naturall loue and duty to my natiue Countrie and your proper inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in my worke as gouerning that Cittie, whose Historie is my subiect; and though I know, that such a Cittie-subiect cannot want enuie in court and countrie: yet if your honour vouch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afe it your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious acceptance, I craue no further fauour of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, then within the liberty of my natiue London to liue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours most humbly deuoted, <hi>Richard Niccolls.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL FAVOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RERS OF ARTES AND</hi> FOLLOWERS OF ARMES, the Captaines of the late Musters and to the rest of the Societie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons hopefull <hi>Infantrie.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen on that plot of ground I you beheld,</l>
               <l>(Braue brood of Mars) where Mars of yore did lead</l>
               <l>The <hi>
                     <seg rend="sup">a</seg>
                  </hi> Romane troopes, me thought,<note n="b" place="margin">For this see the <hi>10.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.</hi> pag.</note> ye stood in field</l>
               <l>As souldiers from their ashes newly bred,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That thought to sing your prayse inspir'd my Muse</l>
               <l>And first gaue life to this heroique song,</l>
               <l>Which ye that vnderstand can not abuse;</l>
               <l>Braue minded Mars the Muses will not wrong:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phillips</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Alexander the great.</note> great sonne, great souldier of his time,</l>
               <l>Who wepte, because poore <hi>Homer</hi> did not liue</l>
               <l>To sing his life, to<note n="c" place="margin">Cherillus.</note> one, that could but rime</l>
               <l>Yet good regard for each good verse did giue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke what he did and what that Monarch was,</l>
               <l>So shall my verse not vnregarded passe.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Euer well-wishing to you and your noble exercise,</hi> Richard Nicolls.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:4"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST WORTHIE GENTLEMAN CAPTAINE EDMVND Panton Captaine and Leader to our Londons hopefull <hi>Infantrie.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>COnceit not (Worthie Sir) that selfe conceit</l>
               <l>Did giue my humble Muse aspiring wings,</l>
               <l>To mount your spheare of <hi>Mars,</hi> affection great</l>
               <l>To your great worth, is cause of what she sings,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To you prime Mouer of that martiall spheare,</l>
               <l>Wherein so many sparkes of hope do shine,</l>
               <l>She first doth sing, in hope your gentle eare</l>
               <l>Will giue free way to these <hi>Essayes</hi> of mine:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where if you finde ought good, or ought amisse,</l>
               <l>Will to doe well in either I haue showne;</l>
               <l>If good, or bad, or both, I craue but this,</l>
               <l>That as you find it, you will make it knowne:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But (gentle Sir) first deigne to reade: then iudge,</l>
               <l>And what your censure is, I will not grudge.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to be commanded <hi>R. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177744:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince in this vncharitable age, most men in suspending their iudgements, do more often shoote their arrowes of censure out of the bow of passion, then reason, I do here set foorth this <hi>Essay</hi> of my Poem, as a common Butt, with a resolution expecting more arrowes of enuie then loue; yet if any ingenuous, more out of their owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, then perhaps my desert, shall here thinke any thing well done; let them know that I haue endeuoured to doe well, as one that loues doing well for it selfe, more then for thankes; If the enuious who thinke any thing absurd in another, which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count excellent in themselues, shall condemne this my endeauor, to honour my natiue London, and that exercise of Armes, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the industrie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d expence of her hopefull <hi>Infantrie</hi> as vaine: yet can they not, if they will say it is great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anitie, but euen out of enuie wih all say it is great loue, my loue to them their worth, and practise, hauing beene the first c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>use that gaue life to this labour. To those that except against the title of my worke which I call <hi>Londons Artillerie,</hi> because it is an impropriety of speech, not communicable to those of this praise worthie So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, I answer, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m constrained to impose this terme vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the, both because by the ignorant vulgar, they are generally so called, and the French word <hi>Infantrie</hi> with other more sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant &amp; proper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re scarse intelligible to any common Reader. The su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iect or matter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m take thus: armes being none of my profession of that I haue onely la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e downe these few po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions First <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> nor shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vse armes for his art or tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: that euery s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate or commonwealth should rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy and traine vp their owne natiue people in martiall discipline
<pb facs="tcp:177744:5"/> for their defence, then strangers: That practise and time doe produce both stronger men and better soldiers, then nature &amp;.c. Of London, if any desire to know the aptenesse of scituation, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of soyle, holesomnes of aire, Antiquitie, deriuation of name, honour of Armes, dignitie and vertue of Magistrates, martiall Exercises, natures of vsuall armes both auncient and moderne, in this little worke, as through a glasse they may behold all these reflected frō the light of auncient &amp; authentike authors The order and maner into which I haue digested this little labor is thus, I haue grounded an Inductiō to the ensuing Cantoes, on certain reliques of Roman Antiquity, found in the feild, adioyning to this hopefull Companies Campus Martius, vulgarly called the Artillerie garden, amongst which the Image of <hi>Minerua</hi> being one, I haue made her, beeing President of arts and armes, the Author of my Poem, deuided into ten <hi>Cantoes,</hi> to which <hi>I</hi> haue adioyned certain notes of Illustration in Prose, not out of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected singularity, it being a thing not vsuall, but both to explain such places, which to the ignorant and perhaps to some, who think themselues no common Readers, may seeme difficult, and also to confirme such points of historie, by the testimonie of approoued Authors, which in my Poem may seeme doubtfull: For thy better instruction (gentle Reader) I intreate thee to obserue, that this marke "against any verse stands as a note of direction to the same verse in the Illustrations. Thus hoping a charitable censure, I craue no other reward for my paines, but that thou feeding on the fruite of my labor maist well disgest it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177744:5"/>
            <head>LONDONS ARTILLERIE.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>Induction.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen the daies King, our Sommer once begun,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Leo's</hi> Inne had lodg'd his golden Sun,</l>
                  <l>And had, to sport himselfe some little space,</l>
                  <l>Heau'ns Dog-starre loosd, to giue the <hi>Lion</hi> chace;<note place="margin">A Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the late drie Summer.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The eager Dogge so hotly did pursue</l>
                  <l>The panting <hi>Lyon,</hi> that the breath, which slew</l>
                  <l>Before his nosthrils, kindled in our aire</l>
                  <l>A fire vnseene, which made the mountains bare,</l>
                  <l>Sing'd vales and plaines, lickt vp the dewes sweet drops,</l>
                  <l>Suckt the trees sap out at their leauy tops:</l>
                  <l>Yet still the starry Curre so thirstie grew,</l>
                  <l>That lakes, ponds, pooles, all plashes drie he drew;</l>
                  <l>The siluer Brookes beneath their banks did shrinke,</l>
                  <l>Earth gap't at heau'n with open mouth for drinke:</l>
                  <l>Riuers, halfe lapt vp by his blaring tong,</l>
                  <l>Scarce quencht the thirst, which his hot stomacke stong</l>
                  <l>By his fierce heate, that humour hid within</l>
                  <l>Our humane bodies, through the porie skin,</l>
                  <l>He did attract so fast in drops of sweate,</l>
                  <l>That men did faint beneath his fierie heate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177744:6"/>
                  <l>And I, that shut vp in my carefull cell,</l>
                  <l>His burning fury by effects could tell,</l>
                  <l>Rose with the Larke, the morns cloud-climing singer,</l>
                  <l>To take the aire, the hot bloods-cold breath-bringer;</l>
                  <l>And on the East of that greene plot of ground,</l>
                  <l>Which Londons<note n="*" place="margin">The Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie yard.</note>
                     <hi>Campus Martius</hi> may be crownd,</l>
                  <l>Where that free troope all voluntary led,</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>Mars</hi> his day, the war-gods dance do tread,</l>
                  <l>I from my natiue (London) walked forth</l>
                  <l>Into that field of yore cald<note n="*" place="margin">The Spittle field.</note>
                     <hi>Lolesworth:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where the fresh aire by winds tost to and fro,</l>
                  <l>Which keepe it vncorrupt, me thought, did show</l>
                  <l>That heau'ns afflictions euer purge the minde</l>
                  <l>Of those, that vnto vertue are inclinde:</l>
                  <l>The Larke, that left her food, her nest, her yong,</l>
                  <l>And early mounting, first with her sweet song,</l>
                  <l>Saluted heau'n, did seeme to bid vs win</l>
                  <l>Helpe from aboue, ere our dayes worke begin;</l>
                  <l>The Strawburie and sent-sweete Violet,</l>
                  <l>Which abiect grew, before mine eyes did set</l>
                  <l>That vnknowne worth, which oftentimes doth dwell</l>
                  <l>With meanest fortunes in a homely cell:</l>
                  <l>The odoriferous Rose, the gardens Queene,</l>
                  <l>Bout whom an hoast of thorny prickes are seene,</l>
                  <l>Said, they must suffer paine, that seeke for honor,</l>
                  <l>Since hard accesse and danger wait vpon her;</l>
                  <l>The bearded Corne, mongst whom the fuller Eare</l>
                  <l>Did bow the head, when they that emptie were</l>
                  <l>Would waue aloft, did shew that vertuous men,</l>
                  <l>The more they haue, the more still humbled ben:</l>
                  <l>On euery creature, natures God hath writ,</l>
                  <l>Instructiue noates to teach the dullest wit.</l>
                  <l>Thus walking on, by chance I cast mine eye</l>
                  <l>Vpon that ancient place, shot vp on hie,</l>
                  <l>Which was by worthy founders raisd of yore,</l>
                  <l>To be an<note n="*" place="margin">Hospitall of Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Spittle.</note> house of mercie to the poore,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177744:6"/>
                  <l>For whose decay, which then I did behold,</l>
                  <l>Thus to my selfe, my griefe I did vnfold,</l>
                  <l>Thou noble relique of that<note n="*" place="margin">Two citizēs of London, of whom see the Illustrations. Decay of the Hospitall.</note> nobler man,</l>
                  <l>And his deare spouse, whose bounteous hands began</l>
                  <l>And finished those workes of praise in thee,</l>
                  <l>Whose like these iron daies doth seldome see;</l>
                  <l>Where are become those almes deeds of the dead,</l>
                  <l>With which so many poore in thee were fed?</l>
                  <l>Or where those lodgings now, which then each night</l>
                  <l>Gaue harbour to so many a wandring wight?</l>
                  <l>Do they abide? alas they all are gone,</l>
                  <l>And nothing left, lesse deafer, then the stone</l>
                  <l>Within thy walls, to hearken to the poore,</l>
                  <l>If they to thee their wretched case deplore.</l>
                  <l>O wofull state of miserable man</l>
                  <l>Once dead, scarce any good or vertue can</l>
                  <l>Liue after death with vs! for such the rage,</l>
                  <l>And the dull blindnesse of this enuious age,</l>
                  <l>That eu'n the shadow of that antique good,</l>
                  <l>That wont to be, is now not vnderstood,</l>
                  <l>And the good deeds themselues of those good men,</l>
                  <l>Are swept away, as they had neuer ben:</l>
                  <l>Alas that vipers-like, we should deuoure</l>
                  <l>The liues of our deare parents, who had powre</l>
                  <l>To liue a leauing name to vs vnkinde</l>
                  <l>In those their workes, which they haue left behinde,</l>
                  <l>Which to the like, might like true lights conduct vs;</l>
                  <l>Examples more then precepts do instruct vs:</l>
                  <l>But that imagination may not thinke,</l>
                  <l>That euer good was there, vnto a sinke</l>
                  <l>Of euill we conuert that plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which then</l>
                  <l>Was the true zealous worke of vertuous men.<note place="margin">Abuse of the same.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For where the aged and the impotent,</l>
                  <l>Liu'd in their actions chast and innocent,</l>
                  <l>Th'vnbridled stalion, breathing furious lust,</l>
                  <l>Prouokes encounters in the <hi>Paphian</hi> ioust</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177744:7"/>
                  <l>And there, where many a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue-teare dropping eye</l>
                  <l>With zealous hands, once lifted vp on hie</l>
                  <l>Vnto the King of heau'n by prayer, were winners</l>
                  <l>Of soules saluation to repentant sinners,</l>
                  <l>Now French-sicke Syrens, and lewd Circe's dwell,</l>
                  <l>Whose lookes are hookes to hale hot blods to hell:</l>
                  <l>O that the buds of youth, that promise much</l>
                  <l>Of timely fruite to follow, by the touch</l>
                  <l>Of Cankers here decaying, should despaire,</l>
                  <l>Who sucking sorth the verdure of their faire,</l>
                  <l>Conuert the sap of their inclinde good will</l>
                  <l>Into the poyson of detested ill;</l>
                  <l>Or that the aged Chrone is suffred here</l>
                  <l>To feed the Cockatrice, who doth appeare</l>
                  <l>No sooner hatcht, but that she runs in hast</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Ʋenus</hi> schoole, where she doth learne at last,</l>
                  <l>With pestilentiall lookes and banefull breath,</l>
                  <l>In youth to blast poore modestie to death.</l>
                  <l>To you (graue Lord) therefore, who for this yeare,</l>
                  <l>Do <hi>Atlas</hi>-like vpon your shoulders beare</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Londons</hi> heau'n; the <hi>Genius</hi> of this place,</l>
                  <l>By me doth beg redresse for such disgrace,</l>
                  <l>Lest <hi>Englands</hi> pearle not onely beare the staine</l>
                  <l>Of being blemisht; but seeme so prophane,</l>
                  <l>That her concurrent enuious <hi>Rome</hi> may say,</l>
                  <l>Where vertue was, now vice beares supreame sway,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No sooner did my Muse, vrg'd by the wrong,</l>
                  <l>Of these bad dayes, end her Satyricke song,</l>
                  <l>But looking backe, behind me, I beheld</l>
                  <l>One, that had all this time himselfe conceald:</l>
                  <l>His garbe was Souldier-like, so was his gate;</l>
                  <l>His weeds though meane, were comely: yet his state</l>
                  <l>As 'tis the souldiers portion now, was poore,</l>
                  <l>His lookes did say his purse had little store,</l>
                  <l>And yet vpon his brow beneath his hat</l>
                  <l>Temperd with mildnesse, manly sternesse sat,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177744:7"/>
                  <l>Denouncing peace to those, that peace allowd,</l>
                  <l>And warre to those, that would be vainly prowd;</l>
                  <l>Who, when within the reach of voyce he came,</l>
                  <l>Saluting me, his purpose thus did frame,</l>
                  <l>Good time of day, Sir, be it no offence,</l>
                  <l>That bluntly I intreate you to dispence,</l>
                  <l>With your owne meditations for a space,</l>
                  <l>That I to you may tell the worlds disgrace</l>
                  <l>To men of armes; we often by discourse</l>
                  <l>Finde ease of heart; and I do reade remorse</l>
                  <l>Writ in your lookes, of which my wrongs reueald</l>
                  <l>May find some comfort: Humane griefes conceald,</l>
                  <l>Are in great thoughts, like strong wines, that will rent</l>
                  <l>The caske in peeces, if they want their vent.</l>
                  <l>Alas Sir, answerd I, what comfort can</l>
                  <l>Expected be from such a naplesse man,</l>
                  <l>Who by the vaine worlds mocke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y is made</l>
                  <l>Your fellow seruant vnto care? words fade,</l>
                  <l>Like false friends leauing vs, and will be found</l>
                  <l>As fruitlesse, to our griefes, as Musicks sound</l>
                  <l>Is to the deafe mans care, onely they feed</l>
                  <l>Our humours for a time; yet after breed,</l>
                  <l>As do dead bodies their owne eaters, cares,</l>
                  <l>That do consume vs; yet no man despaires,</l>
                  <l>That sees his equall with true patience beare</l>
                  <l>The like bad fortune: for now euery where,</l>
                  <l>The Muses pupils, whose profession yet,</l>
                  <l>(Except where Ignorance, as Iudge is set,)</l>
                  <l>Shall ne'r giue place to armes, are made the scorne</l>
                  <l>And scum of time, who though thus left forlorne;</l>
                  <l>Yet like the teeth, that still preparing food,</l>
                  <l>Do hurt themselues to do the body good,<note place="margin">Neglect of learning.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In watchfull studies wasting out their prime</l>
                  <l>And May of youth, grow old before their time,</l>
                  <l>And both their health, their wealth, and wits engage</l>
                  <l>With golden knowledge to enrich this age,</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:177744:8"/>
                  <l>Who strumpet-like, vnthankefull, with a scoffe,</l>
                  <l>Once hauing knowne their worth, doth cast them off,</l>
                  <l>Except they stoope like Panders to the time,</l>
                  <l>And do partake with it in euery crime:</l>
                  <l>If any noble wit, rauisht with loue,</l>
                  <l>To those diuiner mysteries aboue</l>
                  <l>His talent would apply, he must appeale</l>
                  <l>To some Church-chaffring Chuffe, who will so deale</l>
                  <l>By his Primitias, or some other meane,</l>
                  <l>That the poore Liuing, will be left too leane</l>
                  <l>To liue vpon; except some one disburse</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Leuits</hi> portion out of his owne purse:</l>
                  <l>If any sound, profound, farre-reaching sprite,</l>
                  <l>Whom the deepe Politikes do most delight,</l>
                  <l>Do breake his quiet sleepes to serue the State,</l>
                  <l>How many tedious winters must he waire</l>
                  <l>Vpon the taile of Greatnesse, and yet finde</l>
                  <l>Himselfe like him, that seekes to graspe the winde;</l>
                  <l>Mockt and deluded with vaine words so long,</l>
                  <l>Till in olde age death consummate his wrong?</l>
                  <l>(O haplesse brood of great <hi>Apolloes</hi> braine)</l>
                  <l>To what shifts do these times your wits constraint.</l>
                  <l>Some forc't by want to lay by learnings worth,</l>
                  <l>Turne Liuerie men; others, whose yonger birth</l>
                  <l>But little better fortune doth affoord,</l>
                  <l>Must Pedagogize at some great mans boord,</l>
                  <l>And learne true Congeis of some trencher boy,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith to please their Patrons painted toy:</l>
                  <l>Others ill vsing their Dramatike pens</l>
                  <l>To grace the Stage, and promise pleasing Sceans,</l>
                  <l>With the sweete honey of their golden stile,</l>
                  <l>Feed others fat, and sterue themselues the while.</l>
                  <l>Thus then you see, that in the selfe same fate,</l>
                  <l>Both men of arts and armes participate,</l>
                  <l>Which may yeeld comfort, since 'tis some releefe</l>
                  <l>To wretched men, t'haue partners in their greefe.</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177744:8"/>
                  <l>To this, the souldiour sighing, thus reply'd,</l>
                  <l>Ayme, would God, that I in armes had dy'd,</l>
                  <l>Since being poore, and therefore deemd a slaue</l>
                  <l>By the times worldlings, in distresse I haue</l>
                  <l>No other salue to cure my wound of care,</l>
                  <l>But onely what forc't patience can prepare:</l>
                  <l>For since the due of armes we are bereft,</l>
                  <l>What hope of helpe, is to the souldiour left?<note place="margin">Neglect of armes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pride-pampring ease, secure of after harmes,</l>
                  <l>Inchants the warre. God in her wanton armes,</l>
                  <l>And from his helme, now hung vp by the walls,</l>
                  <l>In whose darke concaue Spiders weaue their cauls,</l>
                  <l>His plume is pluckt away, which euery where,</l>
                  <l>Cowards and martiall men alike do were;</l>
                  <l>Who in the steed of Gorget made of steele,</l>
                  <l>Bout their phantastike neckes do fondly wheele</l>
                  <l>That base deuice of yeallow fall and ruffe,</l>
                  <l>As if the patterne of that fierie stuffe,</l>
                  <l>In the true perfect colour, they would take,</l>
                  <l>Which pride shall put on in the burning lake.</l>
                  <l>But soft, I seeme too bitter gainst the times,</l>
                  <l>And some perhaps, who patronize such crimes,</l>
                  <l>Will taxe my plaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as vtterd in despight,</l>
                  <l>Out of a warre-thirst gainst the sweet delight</l>
                  <l>Of blessed peace, which heau'n doth still bestow</l>
                  <l>Vpon our state; but let such fondlings know,</l>
                  <l>I to my countrie, wish no wounds of steele,</l>
                  <l>But such, as now our fruitfull furrowes feele,</l>
                  <l>Onely it grieues my soule to see th'increase</l>
                  <l>And fruite of plentie, which our happie peace,<note place="margin">Pride chiefe author of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in our State.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So long enioyd, could carefully proulde,</l>
                  <l>Deuour'd and eate vp by their wanton pride,</l>
                  <l>Who, like a treacherous: Peere, that bearing sway</l>
                  <l>In state affaires, makes euery one giue way</l>
                  <l>To his designes, fights for our foes at home,</l>
                  <l>That so our selues, our selues may ouercome.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177744:9"/>
                  <l>Tis that (alas) that with selfe-spoyling hand</l>
                  <l>Exhausts the golden treasures of our land,</l>
                  <l>Wastes townes and cities, makes our people bare,</l>
                  <l>Turnes rich men poore, brings poore men to despaire:</l>
                  <l>It is that <hi>Omphale,</hi> that by her charmes,</l>
                  <l>Makes our <hi>Herculean</hi> youth, neglecting armes,</l>
                  <l>Put on the habit, lookes, lockes, pace and face,</l>
                  <l>Of tender women, to their beards disgrace:</l>
                  <l>It is that Harlot, who by lust at length</l>
                  <l>Cuts of the lockes of our young <hi>Sampsons</hi> strength,</l>
                  <l>Giuing the golden gulls of these our dayes</l>
                  <l>An heart, but of an Hart, in bold assayes</l>
                  <l>Fitter swift flight, then fight to vndergoe,</l>
                  <l>Who for themselues do no true valour know,</l>
                  <l>Sleight the poore souldiour, as debosht and base:</l>
                  <l>Yet if grim-visag'd warre should shew his face,</l>
                  <l>Such Fops to meanest souldiours, arm'd in steele,</l>
                  <l>As vnto Gods for helpe would basely kneele;</l>
                  <l>Tis not sweete peace (which is and hath bene giuen</l>
                  <l>Onely to those, that are belou'd of heauen,</l>
                  <l>Gainst which the vulgar vainly doth inuay)</l>
                  <l>That is the cause of martiall mens decay;</l>
                  <l>For since their swords do purchase peace from farre,</l>
                  <l>Wise peace should keepe them still, to keepe out warre:</l>
                  <l>Those lazie <hi>Lozels,</hi> that on soft downe beds,</l>
                  <l>Till noone day laying their phantasticke heads</l>
                  <l>Vnto the pillow, study and deuise</l>
                  <l>On some quaint English, French, or Tuscan guise,</l>
                  <l>Who to maintaine strange fashions, and new cuts,</l>
                  <l>Do wring their poore racke-rented tenants guts;</l>
                  <l>Who kindling lust at euery females eye,</l>
                  <l>Fell forrests, woods, make lands and lordships flie,</l>
                  <l>T'incense chast Matrons to vnchast desier,</l>
                  <l>And burne their beauties vp in <hi>Paphian</hi> fier;</l>
                  <l>Who greedy after gaine, turne peopled townes</l>
                  <l>Vnto poore sheepe-coates, to increase their crownes,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177744:9"/>
                  <l>Are they, whom our long happy peace doth pricke</l>
                  <l>With such luxurious plenty, that they kicke</l>
                  <l>At heau'n forgot, and in such gluttonies</l>
                  <l>Loath peace it selfe; yet men at armes despise;</l>
                  <l>These are our kingdomes troubled seas, wherein</l>
                  <l>Tost by blacke vice, waue hunteth waue of sinne,</l>
                  <l>Nought casting on our coast of Brittannie,</l>
                  <l>But weeds and froth of soule impietie;</l>
                  <l>O, that such subiects (since vpon the throne</l>
                  <l>Kings sit as lights, for vs to looke vpon)</l>
                  <l>In decent habit, and right vse of things,</l>
                  <l>Would imitate the glory of all kings,</l>
                  <l>Our learned Soueraigne, vsing his increase</l>
                  <l>With modest hand, in calme of this our peace!</l>
                  <l>Who (our true <hi>Solomon</hi> to peace inclinde,</l>
                  <l>Whose royall<note n="*" place="margin">Beati Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici.</note> Motto shewes his royall minde)</l>
                  <l>Sayes to the world by his world-wondred name,</l>
                  <l>Vnto my kingdome,<note n="*" place="margin">Iames Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wart. <hi>Anagram.</hi> A sweet rest I am.</note>
                     <hi>A sweet rest I am.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But cease my bootlesse plaints, and let me liue</l>
                  <l>Safe to mine owne thoughts, lest I hap to giue</l>
                  <l>(Seeking to cure my carelesse countries crimes)</l>
                  <l>Pils farre too bitter for these sinne-sicke times;</l>
                  <l>I know rude souldiers are too rough to please</l>
                  <l>This dainty age, the darling of soft ease;</l>
                  <l>And best it is in silence to lament</l>
                  <l>That euill, which our plaints cannot preuent.</l>
                  <l>This said, we heard through ecchoes shrill rebound</l>
                  <l>The drums dull spirit-animating sound,</l>
                  <l>And volleyes of thicke shot, in thunder spending</l>
                  <l>Their fiery spleene, through clouds of smoke ascēding;</l>
                  <l>At which amaz'd, the souldier startled stood</l>
                  <l>As out of passions dreame, wakt with the good</l>
                  <l>Of happy tidings, and with greedy eye</l>
                  <l>Searching about, askt whence it was, and why;</l>
                  <l>To whom, I thus; this is that<note n="*" place="margin">The field lying on the East side of the Artillery yard.</note> famous field,</l>
                  <l>VVhich once her bosome did for buriall yeeld</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:177744:10"/>
                  <l>To Romane Victors, after that the power</l>
                  <l>Of ciuill warre, which doth it selfe deuoure,</l>
                  <l>Had brought the Brittaine by the fatall stroke</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Caesars</hi> sword, beneath the Romane yoke:</l>
                  <l>For here olde Rome (the worlds proud mistres) brought</l>
                  <l>Her youth vp in the sleights of warre, and taught</l>
                  <l>Euen in this place, the souldiers bloody game,</l>
                  <l>For which they grew so farre renownd in fame,</l>
                  <l>Where she hath kept in many a sacred vrne</l>
                  <l>The Romane reliques, which the pile did burne</l>
                  <l>In funerall flame, before those bloody dayes,</l>
                  <l>That great <hi>Ʋesp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sian</hi> wore th'imperiall bayes,</l>
                  <l>When his braue sonne, that heau'n-sent raging Lion</l>
                  <l>Pitcht his prowd Eagles on the walls of Sion.</l>
                  <l>And as the King of Prophets did foresee,</l>
                  <l>There left no stone vpon a stone to bee;</l>
                  <l>And since that time, vntill these later dayes,</l>
                  <l>Which do neglect all monuments of prayse,</l>
                  <l>Those Romane reliques here reseru'd haue beene,</l>
                  <l>Though now of them no signes are to be seene:</l>
                  <l>But rest, ye wronged ghosts of Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns gone,</l>
                  <l>And since the fatall flood, where euery one</l>
                  <l>As w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aried, leaues his mortall loade at last,</l>
                  <l>Ye long agoe t'<hi>Elisium</hi> plaines haue past,</l>
                  <l>Let not that wrong late done, alas therefore,</l>
                  <l>Vnto your graues, now grieue you any more:</l>
                  <l>Englands<note n="*" place="margin">London so c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld by the Romans, of which in the <hi>7.</hi> Canto.</note>
                     <hi>Augusta,</hi> our fame-farre spread citty</l>
                  <l>Out of your scatterd ashes, as in pitty</l>
                  <l>Of your dead memory, with her kinde hand</l>
                  <l>Hath raisd a<note n="*" place="margin">The compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, of whō see to the <hi>2.</hi> Canto.</note>
                     <hi>Phoenix</hi>-like faire martiall band,</l>
                  <l>Who in that field, where your could graues hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ben</l>
                  <l>So long conceald from knowledge of all men,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Cadmus</hi> bone-bred broode in braue aray,</l>
                  <l>As borne in armes do march each <hi>Mars</hi> his day.</l>
                  <l>To this, the souldier smiling, silence brake,</l>
                  <l>And knowing not their worth, of whom he spake,</l>
                  <l>Said, can soft slakes of wooll, or tennis balles,</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177744:10"/>
                  <l>Like iron bullets, batter strongest walles?</l>
                  <l>Or can the dull sword, made of lead, preuaile</l>
                  <l>Like temperd steele, to pierce the iron male?</l>
                  <l>Or can your cittie people tender bred,</l>
                  <l>Who in the lap of ease are dayly fed,</l>
                  <l>Like souldiers, who to no afflictions yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Brooke the sharpe brunts of warre in bloody field!</l>
                  <l>O, that those auncient Romans, vnto whom</l>
                  <l>The bosome of this field did serue for tombe,</l>
                  <l>Suruiu'd to see, how you this place extoll,</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Remus</hi> sure, would leape the lostie wall</l>
                  <l>Of this your cittie, and would laugh to see</l>
                  <l>The discipline of her Artillerie.</l>
                  <l>To heare these bitter words of proud disdaine,</l>
                  <l>I mou'd in minde, no longer could refraine</l>
                  <l>To checke his errour; but before I spake,</l>
                  <l>The earth beneath our feet began to quake,</l>
                  <l>The heau'ns did thunder, and the cheerefull light</l>
                  <l>Of the noone day did turne to darkesome night,</l>
                  <l>At which, as we amazed stood, from farre</l>
                  <l>"<hi>Ioues</hi> braine-borne <hi>Pallas,</hi> President of warre,<note place="margin">A description of Pallas.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom heau'ns swift whirl-windes on their wings did beare,</l>
                  <l>Leapt on the earth, and shooke her lengthfull speare;</l>
                  <l>A mightie shield, she bore in her left hand,</l>
                  <l>Two <hi>Gorgon</hi>-like grim heads embost, did stand</l>
                  <l>Vpon her breast-plate, proofe gainst dangers doubt,</l>
                  <l>With curious skill engrauen all about;</l>
                  <l>Beneath her helmet, horrid all with gold,</l>
                  <l>Her virgin face, most goodly to behold;</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the golden trammels of her haire,</l>
                  <l>On either side downe flowing, did appeare</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sol,</hi> that day, when rough winds he foregoes,</l>
                  <l>Twixt two hils west a ruddy count'nance showes:</l>
                  <l>Her dreadfull lookes the lightnings flash resembling,</l>
                  <l>She fixt on vs, and as we both stood trembling;</l>
                  <l>Being almost stricken dead with feare and wonder,</l>
                  <l>At last she thus brake foorth in voyce of thunder.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:177744:11"/>
               <head>Illustration.</head>
               <p>ENdeauour in a Writer to please and winne praise, without respect to the truth, carrying with it the fowle note of seruilitie, I here disclaime: and that my Muse was not inspired with a furie to flatter her natiue London, let the testimony of such Authors (by whom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard hath bene taken, how posteritie should be truely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) make iustifiable that here in plaine prose, which may seeme questionable before in my Poem, and so to the first note.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thou noble relique of that nobler man</l>
                  <l>And his deare spouse—</l>
               </q>
               <p>The first obiect, note-worthie, which fals vnder the eye of my Muse in her mornings walke, is that place, which we vulgarly call the <hi>Spittle;</hi> of which I finde recorded in that industrious Antiquarie (M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ster <hi>Iohn Stowe</hi>) that it was an Hospitall of such reliefe to poore people,<note place="margin">In his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay. p. <hi>168.</hi>
                  </note> that at the suppression of the same, with the Priory in that place, in the reign of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, it was valued to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spend <hi>478.</hi> pounds: in which, besides the ornaments of the Church, and goods pertaining to the house, there were <hi>180.</hi> beds well furnished: It was founded by that worthy Citizen <hi>VValter Brune</hi> and <hi>Rosia</hi> his wife, <hi>anno 1235.</hi> in the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of Saint <hi>Marie Spittle.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177744:11"/>
                  <l>Which once her bosome did for buriall yeeld</l>
                  <l>To Romane victors, —</l>
               </q>
               <p>When the Romans were Lords of Brittain, in this field (as in al other places, according to the law of their <hi>12.</hi> tables which you may reade at large in<note n="b" place="margin">De legibus lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi>) they did bury their dead hard by the cittie, as in a publicke or militarie place. Of which, that great<note n="c" place="margin">Camden in Trino. p. <hi>380.</hi>
                  </note> Dictator of Antiquitie, saith thus, <hi>In quorum campis, dum haec scriberemus, eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasunt multa vasa sepulchralia, sigilla &amp; vrnae, in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Claudij, Neronis, Vespasiani &amp;c. nummuli:</hi> That is, in these fields, while wee were writing these things, many funerall vessels, litle images, and vrns were taken vp, in which the moneys of <hi>Claudius, Nero, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spasiā,</hi> &amp; others were foūd. It was a custome thē amōgst the Romans to burne the bodies of their dead, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the ashes in an vrne or funerall pot, as we reade in<note n="d" place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>67.</hi> &amp; <hi>63.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> of the burning <hi>Germanicus</hi> body in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och: whose ashes, his wife <hi>Agrippina</hi> carried to Rome in a funerall pot; of <hi>Seuerus</hi> funerals at Yorke in<note n="e" place="margin">In Brigant. pag. <hi>627.</hi>
                  </note> Master <hi>Camden,</hi> whose ashes in a golden vrne (some say in a vessell of Marble or Porphyrie) were conueyed to Rome by his wife <hi>Iulia</hi> and his sonnes <hi>Antoninus</hi> and <hi>Geta.</hi> But of the finding these Roman reliques, which was, whē this field was broken vp for clay to make bricke, <hi>anno E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liza. 22.</hi> you may reade at large in Master<note n="f" place="margin">In his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay. pag. <hi>130.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Stowe,</hi> to whom I the rather referre you, because he was present at the digging vp of the same.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—and taught</l>
                  <l>Euen in this place the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldiers bloody game.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To my coniecture (I doe not importune your beliefe) yet since Londō, not greatly famous by the name of a Colony which are the expresse words of<note n="g" place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tacitus,</hi> was called
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177744:12"/>
                  <hi>Augusta,</hi> and as some thinke, of the Legion <hi>Augusta,</hi> which there soiourned:<note n="h" place="margin">Raph. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. in his <hi>2.</hi> booke of the description of Brittaine.</note> this Field may seeme to haue bin their <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> or place of military exercise; both, because in the same such Monuments of theirs haue beene lately found, and they, as I before noted, according to the law of their twelue Tables, did burne their dead in military places.</p>
               <q>"<hi>Ioue's</hi> braine-borne <hi>Pallas,</hi> President of Warre.</q>
               <p>Though this fiction of <hi>Pallas</hi> be warranted, both by the rules of Poesie, and examples of such, the imitation of whom may iustifie it, without exception: yet I haue layd the ground of it vpon the truth: for in this Field, where I began this Induction to my ensuing discourse, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Pallas,</hi> (no meane Dietie amongst men of Artes and Armes) was taken vp at the same time amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Romane Reliques, as <hi>Stow</hi> saith, in the place before quoated.</p>
               <div n="1" type="song">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:177744:12"/>
                  <head>CANTO. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>True Discipline they doe abuse,</l>
                     <l>Who for their Art, their Armes do vse.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>WHat Serpent spits his poyson of defame</l>
                  <l>Gainst Englāds Londō, whose illustrate name,</l>
                  <l>If t'other cities we the same compare,</l>
                  <l>Shines like a <hi>Phoebus</hi> to another starre?</l>
                  <l>Or if to any of this Sea-sieg'd land,</l>
                  <l>It, like a Cedar amongst shrubs doth stand?</l>
                  <l>Or who is this, that Cur-like barking bites</l>
                  <l>The good endeauour of those worthie sprites,</l>
                  <l>Who by their loue to armes in martiall game,</l>
                  <l>And honest arts, do honor our great name?</l>
                  <l>Thou foe to vertue, on whose viperous tong,</l>
                  <l>Malice hath set an edge of vniust wrong</l>
                  <l>To wound their good desert, contend with me,</l>
                  <l>And let vs argue on true souldierie;</l>
                  <l>"The priuate man, that makes his armes, his art,<note place="margin">No mā ought to vse warre, as his art.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As many do, that blindly do conuert</l>
                  <l>True discipline of warre into a trade,</l>
                  <l>As by the dog, that in the pond hath plaid,</l>
                  <l>The water drops are shaken off on shore,</l>
                  <l>When warres are husht, is loft and vsde no more;</l>
                  <l>But he, that vseth armes in time of peace,</l>
                  <l>Onely by practice knowledge to increase</l>
                  <l>In time of warre, when cause doth so constraine,</l>
                  <l>And can returne to his affaires againe,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:177744:13"/>
                  <l>Is the true souldier of those antique times,</l>
                  <l>Deprau'd with no such execrable crimes,</l>
                  <l>As he, that as his function vseth warre,</l>
                  <l>Who haunted with penurious want and care,</l>
                  <l>Through greedy thirst of gaine growes mad with rage,</l>
                  <l>And sparing neither place, nor sexe, nor age,</l>
                  <l>That he in peace may liue, when warfare ends,</l>
                  <l>While warre doth last, despoiles both foes and friends;</l>
                  <l>For this, the faithlesse varlet, turn'd prophane,</l>
                  <l>With sacrilegious hands will not refraine</l>
                  <l>The sacred shrines; but with that cruell<note n="*" place="margin">The Hyaena, a beast coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfetting the voyce of man. Plin. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>30</hi>
                     </note> beast,</l>
                  <l>That after death, doth wretched man molest,</l>
                  <l>Teares vp the dead mans tombe, who did suppose</l>
                  <l>The graue a house, secure from all his foes;</l>
                  <l>For this the infants braines, while it doth call</l>
                  <l>The mothers helpe, he dashes gainst the wall,</l>
                  <l>On which it leaues, at leauing of its breath,</l>
                  <l>The bloody story of its life and death;</l>
                  <l>For this, with murderous blade he makes his way</l>
                  <l>Into the wombe, where once the infant lay,</l>
                  <l>To seeke the gold, which being before denyde,</l>
                  <l>He thought the mother swallowing, there might hide;</l>
                  <l>For this, to saue his life, the countrey Bore,</l>
                  <l>Naked is forc't to flie from his owne store,</l>
                  <l>And to th'oppressor leaues, for one dayes spoyle,</l>
                  <l>What he scarce got in twenty Sommers toyle:</l>
                  <l>All these, and many such, like streames of woe,</l>
                  <l>As from that spring of blood and spoyle, do flowe,</l>
                  <l>Which digging with their swords such men do make,</l>
                  <l>That can, in time of peace, themselues betake</l>
                  <l>To no vocation, but thinke others harms</l>
                  <l>Their cheifest good, and count their art their armes.</l>
                  <l>Thou onely<note n="*" place="margin">Carthage.</note> glory of that <hi>Affricke</hi> shore,</l>
                  <l>Where once thou didst thy <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dos</hi> death deplore,</l>
                  <l>And after stoutly didst prowd <hi>Rome</hi> oppose,</l>
                  <l>Lifting thy Scepter t'her Imperiall nose,</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177744:13"/>
                  <l>Be thou a witnesse of that wofull scarre,</l>
                  <l>Giuen by thine owne<note n="*" place="margin">Matho and Spendio two rebellious Captaines. Nic. Mach. de arte bell. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> sonnes in ciuill warre,</l>
                  <l>Who when they first the Romane force did feele,</l>
                  <l>And brauely had repulsed steele with steele,</l>
                  <l>When foes were gone, and thou hadst thy desier,</l>
                  <l>Hauing no trade, to which they should retier,</l>
                  <l>Did turne vpon thee, and thy sides did gore</l>
                  <l>With deeper wounds, then Rome had done before:</l>
                  <l>And thou, faire Italie, the hony spot</l>
                  <l>Of Europes bounds, the worlds sweet garden plot,</l>
                  <l>Did not these moderne dayes thy beauty staine,</l>
                  <l>With the deare blood of thine owne children slaine,</l>
                  <l>By thine owne souldiers, who thy peace being made,<note place="margin">Fra. Guic. Hist. lib. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Except their armes, had then no other trade?</l>
                  <l>O that such men, should boast themselues to be</l>
                  <l>The verie life and soule of souldierie!</l>
                  <l>Yet by their deeds deface the souldiers name,</l>
                  <l>With rapine, theft, with beggery and shame.</l>
                  <l>The<note place="margin">Warre makes theeues, and peace hangs them vp.</note> Tuscan Prouerbe like an Oracle</l>
                  <l>Forespeakes their sate, and 'tis a miracle,</l>
                  <l>If he, that in the calme of peace shall make</l>
                  <l>The sword, his spade, his plough-share, forke, or rake,</l>
                  <l>Twist not so many threds of shame, whose strength</l>
                  <l>Shall be of power to strangle him at length;</l>
                  <l>Such discontented spirits, euer like</l>
                  <l>To raging waues, with all their force, do strike</l>
                  <l>Against our rockes of peace, and wanting might</l>
                  <l>To swallow vp the shoare, for very spight</l>
                  <l>Spitting their furie forth in froathy matter,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the same themselues in peeces batter;</l>
                  <l>But the great Captaines of those antique dayes,</l>
                  <l>Whose conqu'ring swords the Romane state did raise</l>
                  <l>To that proud height, that nations farre and wide,</l>
                  <l>Throughout the world, were vassailes to her pride,</l>
                  <l>Bright mirrours are, in whom this age may see</l>
                  <l>The perfect image of true souldierie,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177744:14"/>
                  <l>Who did atchieue their conquests in times past,</l>
                  <l>With such swift hand, as if they had made hast</l>
                  <l>In all the warres committed to their cares,</l>
                  <l>To make returne vnto their owne affaires:</l>
                  <l>He then, that when warres trumpet ceaseth, can</l>
                  <l>Returne to his owne function, is the man</l>
                  <l>Worthy to manage armes; and such were held</l>
                  <l>In former times, fit souldiers for the field;</l>
                  <l>Such men, like Bees make <hi>Mars</hi> his helme an hiue,</l>
                  <l>Where hony-combs of rest they do contriue:</l>
                  <l>So fighting, that from fighting they may cease,</l>
                  <l>The end, at which good souldiers aime, is peace;</l>
                  <l>And such those schollers are, that do belong</l>
                  <l>T'our schoole of <hi>Mars,</hi> of whom in our next song.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177744:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> The priuate man, that makes his armes, his art.</head>
               <p>IN the youth of the Romane Monarchie, when the slower of her glory began to grow to perfection, not onely, he that made souldierie, his trade; but according to that most learned and elegant<note n="a" place="margin">Sir Henrie Sauill.</note> translator of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> in his view of military mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of <hi>Dionysius lib. 2. Histrionica</hi> and all of sedentary, mechanicall, &amp; voluptuarie arts, were disabled to be Legiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie souldiers; amongst whom, none were enrolled but <hi>ciues Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani, ingenui, artis Iudicrae expertes.</hi> Agriculture was chiefly allowed, as the onely nource of fit men for seruice in warre, they being in peace good husbandmen, and in war good souldiers. No man in their opinion, being more dangerous to a state, then he, which maketh souldierie his occupation or trade: of this, we haue an example of that famous husbandman <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Quintius Cincinnatus,</hi> to whom being at plough, as<note n="b" place="margin">Cato Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior.</note>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> saith, it was shewd, that he was chosen Dictator: this noble Romane, hauing repulsed the <hi>Tuscans, Latins,</hi> and <hi>Volsciās,</hi> ended the war within fifteen dayes, that he might (as he said) the sooner returne to his tillage. The like of this I reade in that worthie Romane <hi>Regulus Attilius,</hi> of whose inuiolate faith to the Carthagenians,<note n="c" place="margin">Offic. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> makes noble mention, who being captaine of the Romane armies in Africa, and hauing often vanquished the enemie, required licence of the Senate to returne home to keepe his possessions, fearing that in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence they were neglected of his husbandmen:<note n="d" place="margin">De re Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stica.</note>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> saith, that <hi>ex agricolis viri fortes, &amp; milites strenuissimi gig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntur, minimeque &amp;c.</hi> Of husbandmen both strong men and valiant souldiers are made, they being least of all euill-thoughted,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177744:15"/> that are exercised in that labor. <hi>Varro lib. 2. &amp; 3. de re Rustica,</hi> writeth much vpō this point; but since these, &amp; the like Romane writers, are so farre remoued from our time, I referre you to<note n="e" place="margin">In his art of warre l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nicholas Machiauell,</hi> a more moderne Author, who affirming, that martiall discipline cannot be iustly vsed, as an art of a priuate subiect or citizen, but of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth or kingdome, vseth a large and copious discourse of the same.</p>
               <div n="2" type="song">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:177744:15"/>
                  <head>CANTO. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>The practice of true Souldierie,</l>
                     <l>By Londons hopefull Infantrie.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>THe enuious Adder, hauing spent his sting,</l>
                  <l>Partakes no more with any poysonous thing;</l>
                  <l>But th'enuious man, when he can do no harme,</l>
                  <l>An others mind with mischiefe seekes to arme.</l>
                  <l>Their exercise of armes, whose worth I sing,</l>
                  <l>Enuie doth seeke to wound with sharpest sting:</l>
                  <l>Yet th'old worlds war-like souldiers, famous knowne,</l>
                  <l>If they did now suruiue, to see their owne</l>
                  <l>Practice of armes, in that free schoole maintaind,</l>
                  <l>In which those hopefull sonnes of <hi>Mars</hi> are traind,</l>
                  <l>Would giue that praise to them, deny'd by none</l>
                  <l>To the same merit, which was once their owne,</l>
                  <l>Whom (thou the Honor of this happy Ile</l>
                  <l>Faire London) to succeeding times maist stile,</l>
                  <l>Thy hopefull <hi>Infantry,</hi> the glittering light</l>
                  <l>Of whose bright armes, in euery strangers sight,</l>
                  <l>Thy name shall more illustrate and vphold,</l>
                  <l>Then all thy glorious shewes of shining gold,</l>
                  <l>Tis not thy wealth, which (O) too oft we know,</l>
                  <l>Betrayes its owner to some treacherous foe,</l>
                  <l>Which both in men of wisedome strength and wit,</l>
                  <l>Masters the Master, that possesseth it,</l>
                  <l>Nor height of walls, of castles or of towers,</l>
                  <l>That shall defend thee against forreine powres,</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177744:16"/>
                  <l>But thine owne sonnes, such as these, now we see</l>
                  <l>Arm'd in bright walls of steele, thy walls must be:</l>
                  <l>Then to this hopefull troope, thy martiall band,</l>
                  <l>Great Queene of citties, stretch thy bounteous hand,</l>
                  <l>And since thou art renown'd for noble arts,</l>
                  <l>As farre as <hi>Titan</hi> shootes his golden darts;</l>
                  <l>So cheare vp this thy chosen infantrie,</l>
                  <l>Giue golden wings vnto their industrie,</l>
                  <l>And hope doth promise thee as great a name</l>
                  <l>In armes, as arts, from their now fligged fame;</l>
                  <l>For pupils in true discipline of warre,</l>
                  <l>Free, not inforc't, they all instructed are,</l>
                  <l>In which they gaine more iudgement with lesse pains,</l>
                  <l>Then any troope, whom strict command constraines;</l>
                  <l>In all our workes a forward mind's good will</l>
                  <l>Finds euer better proofe, then forced skill;</l>
                  <l>And by their industrie, which brings things vnder</l>
                  <l>Our powers reach, which we at first with wonder</l>
                  <l>Do thinke impossible, they doe vphold</l>
                  <l>That knowledge, which in perill makes men bold,</l>
                  <l>Courage in danger doth from knowledge growe,</l>
                  <l>And men lesse feare to do those things they know:</l>
                  <l>They (as our often stroakes make hardest steele)</l>
                  <l>Harden their limbes, that they may seeme to feele</l>
                  <l>No weight of pondrous armes; they learne aright</l>
                  <l>To keepe their rankes, and order for the fight,</l>
                  <l>And vse their weapons to their foes most harmes,</l>
                  <l>Which onely three do make a man of armes;</l>
                  <l>Precepts decreed inuiolate should stand</l>
                  <l>For martiall order in that hopefull band.</l>
                  <l>The factious, turbulent, or idle spirit,</l>
                  <l>Who by some other function doth not merit</l>
                  <l>Of the same commonwealth, they do debarre</l>
                  <l>From their societie, and alwayes are</l>
                  <l>Or should be in their choyce, as circumspect</l>
                  <l>As those old Romans, who did ne're select</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177744:16"/>
                  <l>In their enrolements men, that onely chose</l>
                  <l>Warre for their art, but euer cassing those;</l>
                  <l>And should in discipline, before them lay</l>
                  <l>"That mysterie of Romane state, which they,</l>
                  <l>Whose skill in armes, no nation yet surmounted</l>
                  <l>The forme and essence of a souldier counted;</l>
                  <l>Which if they keepe and kicke not at command,</l>
                  <l>(The life of order) in a martiall band,</l>
                  <l>This brood of <hi>Mars,</hi> like liuing sparks of warre,</l>
                  <l>As the small imbers, which extracted are</l>
                  <l>From the dead ashes, that conceale the same,</l>
                  <l>By often puffes of breath begin to flame;</l>
                  <l>From light of long-neglected discipline,</l>
                  <l>Late kindled by braue spirits doth so shine,</l>
                  <l>That if this age, adde sewell to the same,</l>
                  <l>T'will reach the cloudes vpon the wings of fame:</l>
                  <l>But here perhaps, one of that roaring sect,</l>
                  <l>(Who doth vsurpe a souldier-like respect,</l>
                  <l>Some seeming Martialist, whose spit-like blade</l>
                  <l>Hangs by his side, as th'ensigne of his trade,</l>
                  <l>Whose stiffe mustachios, Porcupine-like haires,</l>
                  <l>Do seeme to whisper mischiefe in his eares)</l>
                  <l>Will aske, why he, or such, who, as he knowes</l>
                  <l>Hath often banded bullets gainst our foes,</l>
                  <l>And in the field haue sometimes had command,</l>
                  <l>Excluded be from being of this band;</l>
                  <l>Why rather in their place, that do apply</l>
                  <l>Themselues vnto this practice, are the fry</l>
                  <l>Of gallant gentrie not aduanc'd, who can</l>
                  <l>And would giue count'nance to the martiall man;</l>
                  <l>Thus argues he; but shall the<note n="*" place="margin">A Citie for her defence ought in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to imploy her owne ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens not strangers.</note> sheapheard yeeld</l>
                  <l>The keeping of his flocke in open field</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Wolfe, though he should promise faire,</l>
                  <l>Or trust it to his Dogs approued care?</l>
                  <l>Or shall the father of a familie,</l>
                  <l>Whose life the dread of death doth terrifie,</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177744:17"/>
                  <l>Commit his safetie to a man vnknowne,</l>
                  <l>Or to a sonne, borne naturally his owne?</l>
                  <l>No trust, where strife and enuie fosterd be,</l>
                  <l>Strangers and natiue borne do nere agree:</l>
                  <l>A cittie, at the helme of whose free state</l>
                  <l>Wisedome (the childe of prouidence) doth waite,</l>
                  <l>To be of powre to beate backe forreigne force,</l>
                  <l>As pupils in the schoole of warre, will nourse</l>
                  <l>No stranger, but her owne, more fearing men</l>
                  <l>That aliens are, then her owne citizen.</l>
                  <l>Great kingdomes soone decline, that do repose</l>
                  <l>Their trust in strangers, as next <hi>Canto</hi> showes.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:177744:17"/>
               <head>Illustrations.
<q>
                     <l>—before them lay</l>
                     <l>That mysterie of Romane state—</l>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the enrollement of the souldier, was that mysterie of Romane estate, as it is in that Authors view of milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie matters, before quoated out of <hi>Herodian,</hi> The mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie oath, which <hi>Cato</hi> vrgeth in his Epistle to his sonne, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by<note n="a" place="margin">Offic. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cicero,</hi> prohibiting him the fight, being disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his Captaine <hi>Pompilius,</hi> except he renewed the oath, which hee there calleth <hi>militiae sacramentum,</hi> and was so strictly obserued by the Romanes, that <hi>Titus Manlius Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatus</hi> for breach thereof did cause his sonne, a young man of great hope, though he had sought valiantly against the enemie, to be cruelly put to death. This oath is thus layde downe by the Author before mentioned: That they should bee obedient and execute to the vttermost of their power, whatsoeuer should bee commanded them by their Captaines and superiours, by which, it appeares, there was no exception of persons, but the man of the best ranke, being rankt with a souldier, was to giue way to the command of his Captain, as farre, as the meanest of his band.<note n="b" place="margin">Plato.</note> The chiefe praise of a souldier is obedience to his captaine;<note n="c" place="margin">Xenph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note>
                  <hi>Without obedience, neither valiant men, stout horse, or strong armour, worke any good effect.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Plutarc.</note>
                  <hi>Scipio</hi> being asked by one, wherin his hope consisted to conquer Carthage, answered in his soldiers: &amp; being againe asked, why, said, because, if I cōmand, they will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bey; obedience to the captain, &amp; mutuall accord, being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177744:18"/> two strongest sinewes of an armie. Another part of this mysterie was (for here I onely mention so much of it, as meetes with my purpose) that none should contend for precedencie in place, which might be decided by senioritie of time and seruice. The auncient manner of mustering was, that the first man should choose out him for second to stand by him in the battaile, whose custome was to march with him in the same ranke: the second the third, the third a fourth, and so each one should choose his mate vnto the last man. It is<note n="e" place="margin">By Liuy. lib. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> called, <hi>lege sacrata coactus exercitus:</hi> an armie constrained by a sacred law, where men so linkt in loue did fight, though with many hands, yet with one minde. <hi>Xenophon</hi> himselfe being an excellent commander, and describing the Persian muster, saith thus; that <hi>Cyrus</hi> sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted two hundred trained gentlemen, fittest for seruice, euery one of those gentlemen, did choose vnto them foure more gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and so amounting to a thousand: euery gentleman did choose thirtie common souldiers, as ten targets, ten slings, and ten bowes, which number did arise to <hi>31000.</hi> and such a power so collected, was by opinion of Antiquitie thought able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the world; but of this enough.</p>
               <div n="3" type="song">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177744:18"/>
                  <head>CANTO. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>States to be free from foes annoy,</l>
                     <l>Their owne, not strangers should imploy.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>THe state, that thinking to oppose all harmes,</l>
                  <l>Shall foster strangers vp for vse in armes,</l>
                  <l>Is like the simple bird, that sits vpon</l>
                  <l>The Cuckowes bastard egges, which as her owne,</l>
                  <l>She carefully doth hatch beneath her brest,</l>
                  <l>By whom growne slushy, she's at length opprest;</l>
                  <l>But the wise State, that danger to withstand,</l>
                  <l>Doth put her strength of armes into the hand</l>
                  <l>Of her owne sonnes, like the<note n="*" place="margin">The Storke.</note> Thessalian foule,</l>
                  <l>Whose feeble strength, when age doth so controule,</l>
                  <l>That she no more can forrage for her foode,</l>
                  <l>Releiued is by her owne proper broode:</l>
                  <l>While the graue Senate of renowned Rome,</l>
                  <l>Did onely arme their natiue youth at home</l>
                  <l>To guard their walles, they kept their libertie</l>
                  <l>Vntoucht by prowd <hi>Caesarean</hi> tyranny;</l>
                  <l>But when <hi>Octauius</hi> sonne of purpose chose,</l>
                  <l>The stout <hi>Praetorian</hi> souldier to oppose,</l>
                  <l>All doubt of danger, who did ready stand</l>
                  <l>Beneath the walles of Rome with swords in hand,</l>
                  <l>To giue the priuiledge of state the checke,</l>
                  <l>And make the Senate stoope t'<hi>Augustus</hi> becke;</l>
                  <l>Then did the worlds great head, her head decline,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Caesars</hi> cloudie frowne, did dim the shine</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177744:19"/>
                  <l>Of her free state, <hi>Augustus</hi> selfe did feare</l>
                  <l>The sway, which that <hi>Praetorian</hi> band did beare,</l>
                  <l>For to that pitch at last their power rose,</l>
                  <l>That Romes tribunall was at their dispose;</l>
                  <l>But like the curious gallant of our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Why do I wander so farre distant wayes,</l>
                  <l>To seeke this errors blacke effects at Rome,</l>
                  <l>When we (alas) may finde them nearer home:</l>
                  <l>Looke backe vnto this kingdoms ancient heire,</l>
                  <l>The noble Brittane, who with sad despaire</l>
                  <l>Driuen to leaue his Northerne seate forlorne</l>
                  <l>Vnto the barbarous <hi>Pict,</hi> being rent and torne</l>
                  <l>With forreine wounds in <hi>Caesars</hi> warres before,</l>
                  <l>Did send for ayde vnto the German shore;</l>
                  <l>To whose request, the Saxon soone did yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Englands great Ancestor, a <hi>Mars</hi> in field,</l>
                  <l>Whose thirst of glory in the bloody fight,</l>
                  <l>And fame in armes the golden starres did smite;</l>
                  <l>He vanquishing the foe, and being Lord</l>
                  <l>Of many a field, did turne his conquering sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd,</l>
                  <l>Flesht in the Pictish blood and drunke with spoyle,</l>
                  <l>To chase the Brittane from his natiue soyle;</l>
                  <l>Such euer are the miseries of those,</l>
                  <l>"That do in strangers strengths their trust repose:</l>
                  <l>For no such saith, or valour shall be found</l>
                  <l>In him, that for anothers good, is bound</l>
                  <l>To meete with danger, as in him that goes</l>
                  <l>For his owne fortune perill to oppose;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Mercenarie men not truly valiant.</note>The hope of pay and spoyle is that, which can</l>
                  <l>Onely giue wings of courage to the man,</l>
                  <l>Whom intertaind, we mercenarie call,</l>
                  <l>"When pay doth faile, his faith and force doth fall:</l>
                  <l>But he, whose countries care lifts vp his hands</l>
                  <l>Against the common foe, bound by strict bands</l>
                  <l>Of loue to parents, children, wife and friends,</l>
                  <l>Not with a thought respecting those base ends</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:177744:19"/>
                  <l>Of pay, or pray for sight, goes double strong,</l>
                  <l>And Lyon-like to guard his tender yong,</l>
                  <l>No smart of wounds, no feare of fortune feeles,</l>
                  <l>Though bloody dangers dogs him at the heeles;</l>
                  <l>Happy that citie then, who at the brest</l>
                  <l>Of bold <hi>Bellona</hi> in the calme of rest,</l>
                  <l>Fosters such sonnes, vnto whose charge and care,</l>
                  <l>She may commit her trust in time of warre,</l>
                  <l>And not be forc't by frowning foes constraint,</l>
                  <l>To stretch forth golden hands with sad complaint</l>
                  <l>To stipendarie Captaines, and to yeeld</l>
                  <l>Her forces to their conduct for the field;</l>
                  <l>Since such men do preferre their stipend farre</l>
                  <l>Before their good, for whom they manage warre:</l>
                  <l>Th'inconstant plume in such a Chieftaines crest,</l>
                  <l>That beimg but an alien to the rest,<note place="margin">Men merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom he conducts, shall more respect his pay,</l>
                  <l>Then his owne fame or honour, waues that way,</l>
                  <l>Which golden gaine with greatest gale doth blow,</l>
                  <l>For this alike, respecting friend and foe;</l>
                  <l>For this, that people of Gygantike breed,</l>
                  <l>"The Canton'd nation, whom those mountains feed,</l>
                  <l>Whose cloud-brow'd heads, do seeme aspiring high,</l>
                  <l>To dare their neighbouring Alpes to scale the skie,</l>
                  <l>Being stipendarie to the Millaine Prince,</l>
                  <l>Did both in field themselues of faith conuince,</l>
                  <l>Though much implord by him with teares of griefe,</l>
                  <l>Sorrowes last arguments to vrge reliefe,</l>
                  <l>And of the wretched Prince, constraind to ioyne</l>
                  <l>His plate to his too little ready coyne,</l>
                  <l>In part they hauing once receiu'd their pay,</l>
                  <l>Did to his foes the forlorne Duke betray:</l>
                  <l>O that a nation of so noble name,</l>
                  <l>Should brand their worth with this one spot of blame,</l>
                  <l>To set their strength to sale, and euer hold</l>
                  <l>The cause most iust, if ballanced with gold;</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177744:20"/>
                  <l>But if to such, so famous in the field</l>
                  <l>For deeds of armes, we confidence might yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Imployd abroad, yet garrison'd at home,</l>
                  <l>What humaine prouidence could ouercome,</l>
                  <l>The many dangers threatning such a state,</l>
                  <l>Subiected to the hazards of debate,</l>
                  <l>Which euer factiously hath fosterd ben,</l>
                  <l>Twixt th'alien souldier and the cittizen;</l>
                  <l>Watchfull distrust, that hath more eyes and eares</l>
                  <l>Lodg'd in the heart, then be phantasticke feares,</l>
                  <l>Which the worlds obiects can present without,</l>
                  <l>Distracts that cittie with a double doubt;</l>
                  <l>And as a goodly palme whose sappie roote</l>
                  <l>Creeping through earth, doth amorously shoote</l>
                  <l>Into the cristall bosome vnespyde</l>
                  <l>Of some sweete brooke, that by her banke doth glide,</l>
                  <l>Feares both the wanton water, which vnkinde</l>
                  <l>Doth wash away the earth, and the fierce winde,</l>
                  <l>That shakes her body, though they both do giue</l>
                  <l>That life to it, which onely makes it liue:</l>
                  <l>So such a commonwealth, that doth both nourse</l>
                  <l>The alien souldier, and the proper force</l>
                  <l>Of her owne citizens, both which do aime</l>
                  <l>Gainst foes inuasion to defend the same,</l>
                  <l>Both feeles th'oppression of the strangers pride,</l>
                  <l>Which free borne spirits neuer may abide,</l>
                  <l>And at that instant feares, through their constraint,</l>
                  <l>The blod reuenge of her inhabitant:</l>
                  <l>Such was the fate of great <hi>Iudeas</hi> Queene,</l>
                  <l>That heau'n on earth, whose like was neuer seene,</l>
                  <l>Ouer whose head, when in the angry skie</l>
                  <l>Those airie horsemen to and fro did flie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Iosephus.</note>When that fierce face of vengeance dreadfull stood,</l>
                  <l>From heau'n denouncing famine, plague and blood,</l>
                  <l>And that th'Olympian thunderer in his ire</l>
                  <l>Had drawne his mightie sword and did inspire</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:177744:20"/>
                  <l>A spleene of Lions through the Roman hoast,</l>
                  <l>T'auenge the blood of her deare prophets lost,</l>
                  <l>Then did faire Sions forlorne daughter feele,</l>
                  <l>Th'effects of trusting to defensiue steele</l>
                  <l>On strangers backes, who made her channels run</l>
                  <l>With the deare blood of many a slaughterd sonne</l>
                  <l>And they againe in armes t'oppose the wrong</l>
                  <l>Of the seditious souldier farre too strong,</l>
                  <l>Did often offer in a crimson flood</l>
                  <l>Their liues to death, commixt with rebels blood,</l>
                  <l>Twixt whom despoyld, great <hi>Salem</hi> conquerd fell,</l>
                  <l>Whom else to stoope proud Rome could not compell:</l>
                  <l>That cittie then, that vseth but her owne</l>
                  <l>For her defence and safetie, feareth none</l>
                  <l>But her owne citizens, mongst whom, if this</l>
                  <l>Or that mans baser heart shall be submisse</l>
                  <l>To coward feare, yet since no people frame</l>
                  <l>A commonwealth, but can defend the same,</l>
                  <l>Their fainting hands in time of need denyde,</l>
                  <l>By others valour will be soone supplyde;</l>
                  <l>For though soft case as Queene in any state,</l>
                  <l>Their reigning long, makes men effeminate;</l>
                  <l>Yet when that people armes againe shall take,</l>
                  <l>Industrious practise ioyn'd with time, will make</l>
                  <l>The fearefull valiant, and the feeble strong;</l>
                  <l>Which to another <hi>Canto</hi> doth belong.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177744:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> That do in strangers strengths their trust repose.</head>
               <p>MY Muse hauing briefly shewed, what manner of men the Romans did enrolle for souldiers, and after their enrolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the oath of obedience to their Captains, she here shewes how dangerous a thing it is to vse the seruice of stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or to teach them, being thy subiects, the discipline of war.<note n="a" place="margin">Hist. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> at large describing the rebellion of the Batauians, whose seruice the Romans had vsed in their warres, bringeth in their Captaine <hi>Ciuills,</hi> whom he there calleth another <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> encouraging them in their reuolt with many forcible rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; but especially with this one, that they had seene and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the best of the Romanes militarie discipline, and this, when the later Emperours did make many Legionarie strangers, did after turne to the ruine of the Romane state. <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Emperour, saith<note n="b" place="margin">Hen. Sa. out of Zosimus.</note>
                  <hi>Zosimus,</hi> Made Legionaries the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians borne beyond Danubius, whereby it came to passe, that hauing taught strangers their discipline and orders milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, they were enforced at length to surrender the Empire to them, to whom they deliuered their armes.</p>
               <q>"When pay doth faile his faith and force doth fall.</q>
               <p>Mercinarie men are neitheir truly faithfull in peace, nor truely valiant in warre, of whom their is no other assurance, then they finde suretie of their pay, who hauing a courage no lesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile and abiect, then their inuentions are corrupt, fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owe warres for rauine and spoyle, the basest respect that can be in the minde of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177744:21"/>
                  <seg rend="sup">a</seg> souldier. <hi>Nich. Mach.</hi> saith, that those men,<note n="c" place="margin">His art of warre. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> that do willingly serue and are not thy subiects, are alwaies the worst of a prouince, who being of such infamous life and conuersation, that like Owles they flie the light of their owne countrey, doe willingly turne sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendarie to any forraine Prince, of whose disloyaltie hee recites many examples of his time in the warres of Italie. But no man did euer make more wofull experience of infidelitie in mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie men, then <hi>Lodwicke Ssorce</hi> Duke of Millaine, of whom because my Muse giues little light of knowledge, except to those, that before haue read the historie, take it thus.<note n="d" place="margin">Fran. Guic. Hist. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> When <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth (to whom in his old age, the Lady <hi>Marie,</hi> second sister to <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight was giuen in marriage) with the armie of France descended into Italie to inuade Millain, the Dukedome of <hi>Lodwicke Ssorce,</hi> the Count <hi>Caiazze</hi> being the Dukes stipendarie, with the same regiments which he had leuied with his treasure, reuolting, entred into the pay of the French King at his first approach. <hi>Iohn Lewis de Fiesque</hi> with other Captains assignd to him for the defence of Millā, but chiefly <hi>Phillip de Fiesque,</hi> who trained vp and aduanced by the Duke, was left there for the credit and opinion of his faith, did all communicate so farre in that infamie, that they did striue who should first deliuer vp the cittie to the King. The Captain of the castle which was thought impregnable, chosen aboue all others for the reputation of his faith and vertue, not abiding so much as one bullet, deliuered it vp to the French: and lastly, the Duke himselfe, hauing lost so great an estate through their disloyaltie in eight dayes, thinking to expose his last fortunes to the hazard of a battaile, was by the Switzers, whom he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in pay and amongst whom he had deuided his siluer plate, and vessell, wanting coyne to confirme their wauering faiths not onely forsaken in the field, but hauing obtained this last refuge to saue himselfe, all other meanes of escape being taken away, to passe by the French armie disguised amongst them, was as hee marched in asquadron on foote, armed at all points as a Switz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r betrayed by them to his enemies and led prisoner into France, which I haue here layde downe, as a notable example of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177744:22"/> infidelitie of mercenarie men.</p>
               <q>"The Canton'd nations whom those mountains feed.</q>
               <p>The Switzers, a people, which<note n="a" place="margin">Ger. descrip. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> calles the Helue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, a race of men naturally valiant, warlike, and rude, inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the high<note n="b" place="margin">Guic. Hist. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> mountaines of <hi>Iura</hi> called S. <hi>Claudo,</hi> S. <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> and S. <hi>Godat</hi> for the sterilitie of their countrey, more giuen to grazing thē totillage, are deuided into thirteene Cōmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalitie, which they call<note n="c" place="margin">Sleid. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cantons,</hi> and are thus named, <hi>Zutike, Bernes, Lucernae, Vra, Switz, Vnteruald, Glarea, Basille, Soludure, Fribourge, Shaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sian, and Apecelle,</hi> all which are gouerned by seueral magistrates, whom yearly they elect and haue their peculiar lawes, yet hold their Parliaments, generall, wherein they dispute their vniuersall affaires, and when they agree by publike decree to deliuer souldiers to the seruice of any Prince, the Cantons choose a Captaine generall, to whom they giue the banner with the ensigne and name publike. They were sometimes vnder the subiection of the Dukes of Austrich, but being oppressed by their nobilitie, and shaking off the yoake they procured their libertie, being since called Switzers of that towne Switz, which was the first of the Cantons, that did cast off the Empire of the Austrian Dukes, they haue bene famous for naturall valour ioyned with discipline both in defence of their countrey at home, and in seruice abroade; yet saith <hi>Guicciar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> their merit had bene farre greater, if they had set before their eyes an end more noble,<note n="d" place="margin">Sleid. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> then the desire of money. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals of euery Canton were wont to receiue pensions of Princes to follow and fauour their faction, vntill <hi>Zuinglius</hi> in his sermons diswaded them of Zurike from the same, and thus much of that Nation.</p>
               <div n="4" type="song">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:177744:22"/>
                  <head>CANTO IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>Practice doth more then Nature can,</l>
                     <l>In making vp a martiall man.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>OVr cittie people, such as liue secure,</l>
                  <l>Whose soft limbes, neate composture, may endure</l>
                  <l>No hardy proofe, who Snaile-like euer shut</l>
                  <l>Within their walles their heads do seldome put</l>
                  <l>Into the aire, but at each drop of raine</l>
                  <l>And puffe of winde do plucke them in againe,</l>
                  <l>May seeme vnfit for armes, and being men</l>
                  <l>Of trafficke and of trades, too dainty ben</l>
                  <l>To march in stead of silkes, from perfum'd shops,</l>
                  <l>In rugged steele o're ragged mountaines tops:</l>
                  <l>But powrefull vse, times wonder-working dame,<note place="margin">The power of vse &amp; custom</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Labours swift handmaide, foe to sloth and shame,</l>
                  <l>The Nurse of arts, of armes, and all great deeds,</l>
                  <l>Men weake in minde and body both, so feeds</l>
                  <l>With her sweet milke of practise, till they grow</l>
                  <l>Men strong and valiant to resist the foe,</l>
                  <l>And custome, who still harkens to the chime,</l>
                  <l>Which truly guided by the clocke of time,</l>
                  <l>Giues notice, how the shaddow of the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Though it but seeme to creepe, yet swift doth run</l>
                  <l>Through the short howres of the dayes true Diall,</l>
                  <l>Makes, though vnseene with wonder in each triall,</l>
                  <l>Practise vnto perfection faster grow,</l>
                  <l>Then the Suns shaddow through the day can goe,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:177744:23"/>
                  <l>For euery childe that generously bred,</l>
                  <l>Shall be by custome natures sister led</l>
                  <l>To practise vertue, makes that seeme it's owne</l>
                  <l>By nature, which by vse in him is growne</l>
                  <l>Vnto an habit, and though yong in yeares,</l>
                  <l>Anticipates his time, and old appeares</l>
                  <l>In spight of death, though it should blast his flowre</l>
                  <l>Of youthfull May, made old in wisedomes powre,</l>
                  <l>Before youths Aprill blossome can begin</l>
                  <l>To sprout out in the bud vpon his chin,</l>
                  <l>Vertue in youth 'fore age oft merits praise,</l>
                  <l>Better die old in deedes, then old in daies,</l>
                  <l>Then if that custome in the childes, that's yong,</l>
                  <l>Makes the soules faculties oft times more strong</l>
                  <l>In the discusse of reason, then we finde</l>
                  <l>In elder age, much more in men enclinde</l>
                  <l>To vse of of armes, her power she doth show,</l>
                  <l>Making weake limbs mightie in strength to grow,</l>
                  <l>That enemy to sloth the little Ant,</l>
                  <l>Whose dayly labor neuer suffers want,</l>
                  <l>The least of limbe, that nature ere did frame,</l>
                  <l>Who from her industrie deriues her<note n="*" place="margin">Formic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> à ferendis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis dicitur.</note> name,</l>
                  <l>Doth practice first to beare a little graine,</l>
                  <l>Endeuours then a greater to sustaine,</l>
                  <l>And so by carrying to the common store,</l>
                  <l>Graine after graine, which scatterd on the floore,</l>
                  <l>She here and there doth finde, at last alone</l>
                  <l>She beares a body bigger then her owne.</l>
                  <l>"This timely vse the Roman youth did make</l>
                  <l>As nimble, and as light, when they did take</l>
                  <l>The field all arm'd in weightie steele, as when</l>
                  <l>In Tybur swimming, they haue naked ben;</l>
                  <l>And will not now the selfe same cause, produce</l>
                  <l>The same effect, custome and frequent vse</l>
                  <l>Do neuer faile to reach beyond the scope,</l>
                  <l>Of that, which we do aime at in our hope;</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:177744:23"/>
                  <l>Behold how Londons armed <hi>Infantrie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Through practice in true rules of souldierie,</l>
                  <l>By the drums martiall musicke often led,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pirrhic</hi> dance do now distinctly tread,</l>
                  <l>Which if industriously they do pursue,</l>
                  <l>And vse that timely custome, which is due</l>
                  <l>To warre-like practice, in despight of hate,</l>
                  <l>Which euermore vpon desert doth waite,</l>
                  <l>Times finger may engraue their industrie</l>
                  <l>Vpon Fames pillers to posteritie:</l>
                  <l>For practice doth produce more men of worth</l>
                  <l>In wit and strength, then nature can bring forth,</l>
                  <l>Now Natures paps are drie, who like a Nurse</l>
                  <l>Ruth'ned with many yeares, or which is worse,</l>
                  <l>Like to a weake or sickly woman, found</l>
                  <l>Through diet or complexion, most vnsound,</l>
                  <l>Doth with her milke firme strength but seldome giue</l>
                  <l>To vs, that in this latter age do liue,</l>
                  <l>When manly exercise, like holesome foode,</l>
                  <l>Which after sicknesse doth augment the blood,</l>
                  <l>Doth by degrees adde strength to strength so long,</l>
                  <l>Till weaknesse waxeth vigorous and strong,</l>
                  <l>Nor is the rough-hewne rusticke large of lim,</l>
                  <l>For warres affaires to be preferd 'fore him,</l>
                  <l>Whose nature ciuill life hath softer made,</l>
                  <l>Soft things are best, when violence doth inuade,</l>
                  <l>The mightie Babel-builders of our time,</l>
                  <l>Those <hi>Nimredizers,</hi> who to heau'n would clime</l>
                  <l>By bricke and stone, who oft in the conclusion</l>
                  <l>Coine wanting, make another strange confusion</l>
                  <l>Of languages, for building neuer cut</l>
                  <l>The hard ragge from the stonie quarrie, but</l>
                  <l>The softer stone, who seeming for to yeeld</l>
                  <l>To stormie windes, doth best maintaine the field;</l>
                  <l>The greatest force with furie ioyn'd, will faile,</l>
                  <l>When little strength well orderd will preuaile:</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:177744:24"/>
                  <l>Then happy thou, thrise happy cittie, since</l>
                  <l>In thee, as in the chamber of the Prince,</l>
                  <l>A people of such strength so orderd liue,</l>
                  <l>To whom thy honor'd state such lawes do giue,</l>
                  <l>That from <hi>Auroras</hi> bowre to <hi>Zephirs</hi> bed,</l>
                  <l>And whence <hi>Orion</hi> lifts his stormie head</l>
                  <l>Vnto the sloe <hi>Bootes</hi> frozen waine,</l>
                  <l>The eye of heau'n scarce sees the like againe,</l>
                  <l>Gainst whom since enuie, honours ancient foe,</l>
                  <l>Detracting libels all about doth throw,</l>
                  <l>Since I haue told, what souldiers ought to be,</l>
                  <l>And what thy <hi>Infant</hi> troope: I now to thee,</l>
                  <l>Must turne my voyce, and strike so high a string,</l>
                  <l>That I in stately stile thy worth may sing.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:177744:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> "This timely vse the Romane youth did make.</head>
               <p>THe Romanes well knowing the power of vse and practice, did institute their <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> a<note n="a" place="margin">Liu. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> place betwixt Tibur and the old citty, being part of the cittie which now stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, cald after the exile of <hi>Tarquin,</hi> whose field it was, <hi>sàrcos pedión,</hi> of being consecrated vnto <hi>Mars;</hi> in this place,<note n="b" place="margin">Nic. Mach in his art of warre. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> thus they did exercise their youth; they would arme them in plates of steele, which should weigh twise so much as the armour for the field; In stead of a sword they gaue thē a cudgel leaded, farmore heauie which with a target against posts, of purpose fixt in the ground, they did exercise themselues, whereby they were not onely made more expert, nimble and strong; but by vsing their counterfeit armours, which were most heauie, their ordinarie armour did seeme as familiar as their dayly apparrell.</p>
               <p>This one thing likewise is noted by my author, quoated in the margent, that their <hi>Campus Martius</hi> was seated by Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur, that they might being wearied with exercise on land, refresh themselues in the riuer, and thereby learne to swimme, a quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie both commendable and necessarie in a souldier.</p>
               <div n="5" type="song">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:177744:25"/>
                  <head>CANTO. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>London for soyle, for seate, for sight,</l>
                     <l>And darke antiquitie the worlds delight.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>HEr happy state vpon that healthfull soyle,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">A description of London.</note>Is twixt two hills safe bulwarkt from the spoyle</l>
                  <l>Of tower-tearing <hi>Boreas,</hi> and the<note n="*" place="margin">The South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind.</note> Slaue,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lus</hi> lockes vp in his Libian caue;</l>
                  <l>Admitting that fresh ayre, more pure and thin,</l>
                  <l>Which gentle <hi>Zephirs</hi> milder breath brings in:</l>
                  <l>"A goodly<note n="*" place="margin">Paules.</note> phane built by that<note n="*" place="margin">Ethelbert.</note> Kentish King,</l>
                  <l>T'whom first that<note n="*" place="margin">Augustine.</note> Monke, the Christian faith did bring</l>
                  <l>Doth crown her head, whose proud cloud-climing spire</l>
                  <l>Was three times haplesse burnt by heau'nly fire,</l>
                  <l>She holds in one hand, as a siluer dish</l>
                  <l>Of all the dainties appetite can wish.</l>
                  <l>That<note n="*" place="margin">Thames.</note> Prince of streames, who yeelds to those that liue</l>
                  <l>Within her walls, what land and seas can giue:</l>
                  <l>Vpon whose siluer breast, a thousand saile</l>
                  <l>To her proud towres their tops do yearely vale,</l>
                  <l>Bringing rich wares vnto that quiet roade,</l>
                  <l>From Africke, Asia, and their wilde aboade,</l>
                  <l>That naked send about the sunburnt strand,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Zennes</hi> waues yeeld gold amongst the sand.</l>
                  <l>In th'other hand she holds fields, orchyards, bowres,</l>
                  <l>Faire walks, green pastures, gardens fraught with slowrs</l>
                  <l>A glorious robe she weares, giuen vnto her</l>
                  <l>By mightie Princes, that of yere did woe her,</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:177744:25"/>
                  <l>Wrought with faire temples, turrets, courts of kings</l>
                  <l>And Princes houses, deckt with pretious things:</l>
                  <l>Her stately traine stretcht out along the strand</l>
                  <l>Of siluer Thames, is held vp by the hand</l>
                  <l>"Of that faire<note n="*" place="margin">Westminster</note> nymph, whose once poore Thorny place</l>
                  <l>The first<note n="*" place="margin">King Sebert</note> East Saxon Christian first did grace,</l>
                  <l>Who hath from others since that honour wonne,</l>
                  <l>"To crowne our kings vpon the fatall stone.</l>
                  <l>And as a champion to defend her state,</l>
                  <l>Which Eastward open lies to forrein hate,</l>
                  <l>Her royall Tower hoords vp to keepe foes vnder,</l>
                  <l>Treasures of haile shot, lightning, and fierce thunder,</l>
                  <l>"Whose walles the Norman victor first did raise,</l>
                  <l>Which now do stand as trophies of his praise:</l>
                  <l>O famous mirrour of antiquitie,</l>
                  <l>Who can behold thy soyles felicitie?</l>
                  <l>Thy holesome aire, thy wayes so smooth and plaine,</l>
                  <l>That all this land yeelds not the like againe,</l>
                  <l>But must admire thy founders wit; and say,</l>
                  <l>What God-like man did thy foundation lay;</l>
                  <l>But who, alas, can lend me such a light,</l>
                  <l>To leade me on through that Cymerian night,</l>
                  <l>Of darke antiquitie, to find the man,</l>
                  <l>Whose happy hand thy building first began,</l>
                  <l>Humaine coniecture is to weake a ground,</l>
                  <l>On which the truth with confidence may found</l>
                  <l>Antiquities originall, and they</l>
                  <l>Shall euer be at fault, who hunt the way</l>
                  <l>Of common storie, which our trust do blinde;</l>
                  <l>To light beliefe the truth doth seldome finde,</l>
                  <l>Yet did I list with those, that on the tide</l>
                  <l>Of vaine conceite, do saile without a guide</l>
                  <l>Or other <hi>Cynosure,</hi> except the writs</l>
                  <l>Of those, that in the mint of their mad wits,</l>
                  <l>Coyne Princes names, I could from heau'n aboue,</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:177744:26"/>
                  <l>By <hi>Lud,</hi> by <hi>Belin,</hi> and by <hi>Brute</hi> from <hi>Ioue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Draw our descent, as it to me 't were knowne,</l>
                  <l>Whose hand first laid our Londons corner stone,</l>
                  <l>But (my de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re London) me it shall suffice,</l>
                  <l>That North and South, from Suns set to the rise.</l>
                  <l>* Thou art antiquities now standing glorie,</l>
                  <l>Of all the cities in this worlds large storie:</l>
                  <l>Vnmou'd thou art, in greatnesse growing still,</l>
                  <l>As if some powre of more then humane skill</l>
                  <l>A being here had purchasd thee from fate,</l>
                  <l>Vntill this globy fabrickes finall date;</l>
                  <l>For though all cities as in sport and play,</l>
                  <l>Like tennis balls by fortune playd away</l>
                  <l>Throgh change of times, haue chang'd or place or name</l>
                  <l>Yet thou in both art still the happie same:</l>
                  <l>Where is the worlds prowd Mistresse now become,</l>
                  <l>Whose yoake thou once didst beare that first old Rome?</l>
                  <l>Where great<note n="*" place="margin">Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</note> Bizantium, whose inuerted name,</l>
                  <l>Prowd <hi>Ottoman</hi> vsurpes to Europes shame?</l>
                  <l>The first of these her first seate with her fame</l>
                  <l>Long since hath lost; the last hath lost her name:</l>
                  <l>But thou the same in name and site of place,</l>
                  <l>From thy first birth with foes hast found such grace,</l>
                  <l>That Lions like in rage they waxed cold,</l>
                  <l>When they thy virgin beautie did behold;</l>
                  <l>And when our Natiue Brittons fier'd with spleene,</l>
                  <l>T'auenge <hi>Bunduicaes</hi> cause their rauisht Queene,</l>
                  <l>"Did sacke prowd<note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>Albons.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Verulamium,</hi> and cast downe</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Maldon in essex.</note>
                     <hi>Camoladunum</hi> greatest in renowne</l>
                  <l>Of all this Ile,<note n="*" place="margin">Norfolke &amp; Suffolke men.</note> th'<hi>Iceni</hi> that did boyle</l>
                  <l>With furie gainst thy people, did not spoyle</l>
                  <l>Thy then forsaken seate, but did forbeare;</l>
                  <l>Though with the Romane thou confederate were:</l>
                  <l>They knew thy forreine trafficke was the spring,</l>
                  <l>That spread her plenteous streams with each good thing</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:177744:26"/>
                  <l>Through all this land, and with the Oceans spoyle,</l>
                  <l>Boue all their neigbours did enrich their soyle;</l>
                  <l>So farre didst thou all other ports excell</l>
                  <l>For nauigation, as next song shall tell.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:177744:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> "Her happy seate vpon that healthfull soyle.</head>
               <p>WHosoeuer shall iudiciously suruay the excellencie of this Citties scituation, must confesse the first founder to haue had the instructiue helpe of more then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wit. It is seated vpon a rising banke, and yet within a vale; vpon the South &amp; North of it are two hils in almost an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall distance from it, that in the South running somewhat east of it, and being thereby shielded from the fiercer and foggier winds, it lies open to none but the milder west windes. The aire is well knowne vnto all men, that knowe in what degree this famous cittie stands, to be the most temperate of this whole I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, neither doth the pestilence so frequent in it proceede of the vnholesome heauen ouer it, as the ignorant thinke, but of the immoderate gluttonie and excessiue intemperance, both of the inhabitants and all others, that resort thither from all parts of this kingdome; which<note n="a" place="margin">Libel. de situ &amp; nobilitate Londin publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by I. Stowe.</note>
                  <hi>Fitzstephens</hi> writing in the reign of <hi>Henrie</hi> the second thus noted, <hi>Solae pestes Londini sunt immoderata stultorum potatio, &amp;c.</hi> The soyle it sand comixt with grauell abounding in springs; the roade wayes for more then twenty miles euery way vnto it are not onely for the most part smooth and plaine, but in the midst of winter in respect of other places, faire and easie. It borders vpon one of the most famous riuers of the world, of which we will speake in the next Canto, and it so stands, that it could not haue bene seated more commodiously in any other place of the same. For if it had stood more to the West, it should haue lost the ebbing and flowing: if more to the East, nearer to the danger of the enemie, and that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177744:27"/> no Citie of England, but London could minister all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite to the court of the Prince, the Parliament, &amp; that world of people here resident in the foure Tearmes, wee haue an example in the daies of Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> whose displeasure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the cittie of London a certaine courtier discoursing to an Alderman of the cittie, said she intended to remoue the Parliament and Terme to Oxenford, to whom the Alderman wisely answered, that if she did not withall remoue the riuer of Thames, the Terme and Parliament would more misse Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, then London could misse the Terme and Parliament, which after proued true: for Queene <hi>Maries</hi> purpose to remooue them vnto Oxenford was made frustrate, because prouision of things necessarie, especially of Hay could not bee made to serue for ten dayes; though that countrie and the shires adioyning, do yeeld the same as abundantly, as any other part of England and thus much of the scituaton.</p>
               <q>A goodly phane built by that Kentish King.</q>
               <p>The Church of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when Christianitie was receiued amongst the Saxons, which was about the yeare <hi>600.</hi> was buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Ethelbert</hi> king of Kent, the first of the Saxon Princes that receiued the faith, of whom more in the eight Canto. This Church by casualitie of fier, being after burnt<note n="a" place="margin">Sim. Dun.</note> anno. <hi>1087</hi> in the last yeare of the reigne of <hi>William</hi> the first, was againe begun to be new builded by <hi>Mauritius</hi> then Bishop of London, and perfected by those that succeeded him, but it was again fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by lightning<note n="b" place="margin">Abr. Flem ex Fabian.</note> anno. <hi>1444</hi> of <hi>Hen. 6.</hi> ann. <hi>12.</hi> and being againe reedified, it was lastly burnt by lightning an. <hi>1561.</hi> of Queene <hi>Eliz.</hi> an. <hi>3.</hi> It was before it was last burnt, the onely wonder-worthie monument of this kingdome, the spire being iust as high againe, as that which now remaineth; for it is now <hi>260.</hi> foote, and it was then <hi>520</hi> foote: It was thought before the light of the Christian Religion did chace away
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177744:28"/> the Cymerian darkenesse of cursed Paganisme to haue beene the place,<note place="margin">Camden in Trinob.</note> where the temple of <hi>Diana</hi> stood, for she and <hi>Apollo</hi> were chiefe Deities amongst the Brittons.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce poore thorny place</l>
                  <l>The first East Saxon Christian first did grace.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Church of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in Westminster was found by <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> king of the East Saxons, who by the example and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of king <hi>Ethelbert</hi> was conuerted to the Christian faith; This place was by the Saxons of that time called <hi>Thorney,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was all ouergrowne with thornes, and as in that place where now stands the temple of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in time past stood the temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> so in this place, where now stands the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> sometimes stood the temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> out of whose ruines ouerthrowne by<note n="e" place="margin">Camden eodem loco ex Sulcardo.</note> an earthquake in the reigne of the Emperor <hi>Antoninus Pius: Sebert</hi> began the foundatiō of that, which since our kings especially <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, and <hi>Henrie</hi> the seuenth adding to the same as much glorie as art &amp; cost could bestow, is by <hi>Leland</hi> iustly titled <hi>orbis miraculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>To crowne our kings vpon the fatall stone.</q>
               <p>In the Saxon times, the inauguration of our kings was at King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston vpon Thames. For <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour was the first<note n="f" place="margin">Stow in his Suruay.</note> king, that was crowned at Westminster, where the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of his successors hath since continued, but touching the fatall stone, which is now in the chaire at Westminster, brought thither out of Scotland by <hi>Edward</hi> the first as a monument of his absolute victorie. The Scottish<note n="g" place="margin">Hector Boet. If fate doth not deceiue vpon the throne. The Scots shall reigne where they shall find this stone.</note> writers call it <hi>fatale marmor,</hi> vpon which they say that <hi>Gathelus</hi> the first Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish king sat at Brigantia in Galitia, as vpon his regall throne: from thence it was transported into Ireland by <hi>Simon Brech</hi> or <hi>Brechus,</hi> king of those Scottish men there planted, and after into Scotland by <hi>Fergusius</hi> chosen king of the Brittish Scots, who had seated themselues in the North of this Iland, a fatall destinie, as they say, still following this stone, which in this cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177744:28"/> or distich King <hi>Keneth</hi> did cause to be engrauen vpon it.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ni fallat satum, Scoti, quoquunque locatum,</l>
                     <l>Inuenient lapidem, regnare tenentur ibidem.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>"Whose walls the Norman victor first did raise.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The vulgar opinion is, that <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> did build the tower of London, but like to this is that other dreame of his founding the Bath, and that imposture thrust into the Scottish history of his building their <hi>Iulius Hoffe.</hi> For neither was his abode in this Iland so long, as to performe any such worke as it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hy his owne writings, neither did he make any such conquest as to designe any such thing in his absence. The words of<note n="h" place="margin">In the life of Agricola,</note>
                  <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> his owne countriman confirmes it. The first of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, saith he, that entred Brittaine, was <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> who although he terrified the inhabitants with a battail which went on his side and gained the shore; yet may seeme rather to haue shewed the place to posterity, then deliuered to them the possession thereof. It is manifest that <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour was first builder thereof, as appeares by the words of a register booke of the acts of the Bishop of Rochester, which are these, <hi>Gundul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus mandato Gulielmi regis magni, praefuit operi magnae turris London, quo tempore hospitatus est apud quendam Edmerum Burgensem London:</hi> That is, <hi>Gundulphus</hi> the Bishop by the command of king <hi>William</hi> did ouersee the worke of the great Tower of London, at which time he was lodged at the house of <hi>Edmerus</hi> a citizen of London. This was the square or white Tower which<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. Paris.</note>
                  <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus</hi> and <hi>Henrie</hi> the first amplified with a castle on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side towards the Thames, it was after inclosed with a wall or deepe ditch by <hi>William Longchampe</hi> Bishop of Elic a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the rebellious attempts of Prince <hi>Iohn,</hi> his brother king <hi>Richard</hi> being then absent in the land of Palestine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re in many bloody conflicts against the Sarazens he wonne in mortall fame &amp; glorie to his name and countrey.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:177744:29"/>"Thou art antiquities now standing glorie.</q>
               <p>Since the most of our ancient Bards taking the pleasure and libertie of feigning haue rather left vs an image of their owne inuention, then of the truth, wherof they haue written, and since antiquitie cannot be examined by forreine writers, except by such, who writ vpon the state of their own times, leauing <hi>Brute</hi> the supposed builder of this cittie, because neither Greeke nor Romane author writing of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> and of the imagined father of our <hi>Brute, Siluius,</hi> whom some make the sonne of <hi>Ascanius:</hi> others, as that<note n="k" place="margin">Ʋir. Aen. lib. <hi>6.</hi> After thy death, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Aeneas, Lauinia</hi> brings a king forth in the woods and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of kings, who was called <hi>Posthumus,</hi> because borne after his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death.</note> Prince of Poets in this verse, the sonne of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> himselfe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Serum Lauinia coniux,</l>
                  <l>Educet filuis regem, regum{que} parentem,</l>
               </q>
               <p>Yet make no mention of <hi>Brute,</hi> nor of his strange killing of his father in the woods; things if they had bene not easily ouerslipt by writers: I will begin at <hi>Caesar,</hi> whose pen was imployed vpon the state of his owne time. He about <hi>1669.</hi> yeares since, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king search into this Iland, and writing many things of the same calles this place<note n="l" place="margin">Commen. l. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Ciuitas Trinobantum,</hi> that is, not as some thinke, the citie but the state of the <hi>Trinobantes:</hi> for a people vsing the same law: is alwaies by him called <hi>Ciuitas,</hi> so that not onely London, but the two shires of Middlesex and Essex, which after in the time of the Saxō Heptarchie, were called the kingdome of the East Saxons, were then by <hi>Caesar</hi> called <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas Trinobantum,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Annal. lib. <hi>14.</hi> ca. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> calles the people by the same name, inhabiting these parts; yet names this cittie London as now it is, of which in the next Canto. From these words, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas Trinobantum,</hi> they that are tickeled with too much desire to rake their descent out of Troian ashes, do deriue their <hi>Troia noua;</hi> but the opinion of that most reuerent<note n="n" place="margin">Cam. in Trinob.</note> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquarie is, that the word <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> is deriued from the Brittish words <hi>Trenant</hi> and <hi>Nouantes,</hi> both signifying
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177744:29"/> townes and inhabitants in a valley: for London, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex, and Essex, are seated, for the most part, in a vale vpon the riuer of Thames, and therefore the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants then called <hi>Trinobantes,</hi> as they, that did inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite Galloway in Scotland, were for the same cause called in the Brittish tongue <hi>Nouantes,</hi> and as now, they, that dwell beneath the mountaines of the Switzers, are called<note n="o" place="margin">Guic. lib. <hi>10</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Valislens</hi> of inhabiting the vale. But touching the first founder of this Cittie, since the greatest searchers of antiquitie can neither, finde his name, nor what hee was, all other citties, for the most part participating with London in this point, to bee ignorant of their first builder: my Muse here leauing the tradition of common writers to all, that will beleeue them, is content onely to know, that Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is now one of the auncient citties of the world: for though it was in <hi>Caesars</hi> time, as all other citties of this Iland, but a wood, as hee sayth, the trees cut downe and rudely composed for dwelling after their barbarous manner; yet was it at that time of great intercourse with the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of Gallia and other countries, which <hi>Tacitus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, saying, that in the time of <hi>Nero,</hi> it was for concourse of Merchants, and prouision of all things necessarie, of great fame and renowne: to which adding the testimonie of<note n="p" place="margin">Ammianus Marcellinus.</note> an auncient Author, who writing twelue hundred yeares since, called it at that time, a very ancient towne, I affirme that it may boast antiquitie with any now standing, it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the same scituation from times vnknowne, long before <hi>Caesar,</hi> and retaining the same name sixteene hundred yeares knowne, though the name of this Iland were since changed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>"Did sacke proud Verulamium and cast downe</l>
                  <l>Camalodunum —</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verulamium</hi> or <hi>Verlā</hi> and <hi>Camalodunū</hi> vnder the Roman
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177744:30"/> gouernment, by the testimony of <hi>Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Suetonius</hi> were the principall townes where their Legions did reside; the first, out of whose second ruines in the Saxon inuasion, the towne of Saint Albones tooke beginning, was, before the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes entered this Ile, the chiefe seate of <hi>Cassibelline</hi> king of the<note n="q" place="margin">Hertford Buckingham and Bedford shire men.</note> Cattieuchlani, which being expugned by <hi>Caesar,</hi> was after in <hi>Neroes</hi> time, a Municipal city: that other, which is now Maldon in Essex, was the principal seat of <hi>Cunobeline</hi> king of the<note n="r" place="margin">Middlesex and Essex men.</note>. <hi>Trinobantes, Tiberius</hi> then being Emperor: vnto this towne after that<note n="s" place="margin">Diō Cassius</note> ouerthrow giuen by <hi>Aulus Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> to <hi>Cunobilins</hi> sonnes, <hi>Catacratus</hi> and <hi>Togodumnus Claudius Caesar</hi> came in person, to whom an<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tacitus cals it</hi> aram ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternae domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis.</note> altar and temple were there erected, where planting a Colonie, he institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Roman lawes and customes, for which the name of <hi>Britta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> as a title of honour, waas giuen to his sonne, and the Senate at Rome did decree for him a most famous triumph. But of these two townes, the difference betwixt the Municipall towne of <hi>Verulamium</hi> and the Colonie of <hi>Camalodunum,</hi> was, as in an ancient<note n="u" place="margin">Gellius ex oratione D. Hadriani ad Italicenses.</note> author I finde it, thus, <hi>Municipia in ciuitatem extrinsecus assumuntur:</hi> &amp; <hi>Coloniae è ciuitate educuntur:</hi> that is, they that liued in the Municipall or free towne, were such, as being strangers were receiued into the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by the fauour of the Romanes, to be free of Rome as confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, yet vsing their owne lawes, and capiable of any office in state, of which they had their name, <hi>á muneribus capien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> and they that were of the Colonie, were such, as being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of the same cittie, vsed no other then the Romane lawes. Touching the ouerthrow of these two townes, the Brittans a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten yeares after <hi>Claudius Caesar,</hi> grudging the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable tyrannie of the Romans, in the reigne of <hi>Nero,</hi> and especially the<note n="x" place="margin">Norfolke and Suffolke men.</note>
                  <hi>Iceni,</hi> burning with desire to take vengeance, for abuse done to <hi>Bunduica</hi> their Queene, and rauishment of her daughters, did conspire their libertie and reuenge and vnder conduct of their valiant Queene, did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to sacke and spoyle these two townes, as chiefe seates
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177744:30"/> of their seruitude and slauerie, but in furie made, some say<note n="y" place="margin">Tacitus.</note> seuentie thousand, others<note n="z" place="margin">Dion Cassius</note> eighty thousand Romans and confederates passe by the sentence of the sword, but for this I referre you to Historie.</p>
               <div n="6" type="song">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:177744:31"/>
                  <head>CANTO. VI</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>Whence London doth deriue her name,</l>
                     <l>Her nauall forces wonted fame.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>BEfore victorious <hi>Caesar</hi> left the Gaules,</l>
                  <l>And did with wonder view the huge white walls,</l>
                  <l>With which the stormie <hi>Neptune</hi> doth inclose</l>
                  <l>His loued Albion, safe from forreine foes;</l>
                  <l>Londons faire bosome was a harbour knowne</l>
                  <l>To those, that first did hale the sailes, and growne</l>
                  <l>To catch the winde, to carry them away,</l>
                  <l>From raging seas, that sought their liues decay:</l>
                  <l>O what a noursing mother hast thou ben,</l>
                  <l>To noble nauigation and those men,</l>
                  <l>That by their art th'vnweldie Oake do bring</l>
                  <l>To flie as fast, as birds of swiftest wing,</l>
                  <l>And o're the Seas to dance do teach the wood,</l>
                  <l>That in the forrest once vnmoued stood,</l>
                  <l>Some more then man, or some prophetik spirit</l>
                  <l>Gaue thee thy name, foreseeing, thou wouldst merit</l>
                  <l>The same from others citties, knowing this</l>
                  <l>"London in sence a nauall cittie is:</l>
                  <l>For once not he, that doth command the shores</l>
                  <l>From hot Iberia to the curled Mores,</l>
                  <l>Could shew so faire a fleete, and which had wonne</l>
                  <l>The seas large Empire, as thy Thames hath done:</l>
                  <l>For this our virgine-Queene, who Goddesse-like</l>
                  <l>That sonne of Babylon did thunder strike,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:177744:31"/>
                  <l>With terror of her name, did hold thee deare;</l>
                  <l>For all her happie daies, who durst appeare</l>
                  <l>Of any, that do grudge thy growing fame</l>
                  <l>To ope their mouths against great Londons name;</l>
                  <l>That sympathie, which like a loue diuine</l>
                  <l>The Steele and Load-stone doth so fast combine,</l>
                  <l>Was not so great, as that, which was betweene</l>
                  <l>Thy loyall subiects and that royall Queene;</l>
                  <l>The nimble Barkes of thy triumphant fleete,</l>
                  <l>When with th'lberian Giants they did meete,<note n="*" place="margin">Great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madaes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to the shores in thunder oft haue told,</l>
                  <l>Their battailes fought with them for Indian gold,</l>
                  <l>Haue tooke the scepter of the seas command,</l>
                  <l>And put it into their <hi>Elizaes</hi> hand;</l>
                  <l>Oft, as faire virgins in a <hi>Chorus</hi> led,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the musickes sound do dainty tread,</l>
                  <l>Barke after Barke, thy nauie day by day,</l>
                  <l>Fraught with rich spoyles from hot <hi>America,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vpon the waues to thy safe harbour bound,</l>
                  <l>Haue danc'd along the strand to trumpets sound,</l>
                  <l>And glad of dangers past, in passing by</l>
                  <l>Those pleasant woods, which farre off they might eye</l>
                  <l>"Vpon that fruitfull countries hils, the key</l>
                  <l>That opens Englands ports vpon the sea,</l>
                  <l>Vnto that virgin in a voyce of thunder,</l>
                  <l>Haue spoke their dutie, when their sails came vnder</l>
                  <l>"That good Dukes house, which now <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
                     </hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Greenwich</note> green banke names</l>
                  <l>Whose princely towres doth ouerlook the Thames</l>
                  <l>But where are now those many barks become</l>
                  <l>That in this riuers roade could scarce find rome;</l>
                  <l>Or where great <hi>Neptunes</hi> sonnes, of whom such store,</l>
                  <l>He did beget vpon our fruitfull shore?</l>
                  <l>Braue wrastlers with the wind, whose skill can saue</l>
                  <l>Themselues from trip of euery dangerous waue,</l>
                  <l>Do they (as some do thinke) each yeare decay</l>
                  <l>By desperate diuing in the Indian sea?</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177744:32"/>
                  <l>Or doth some greedy-minded <hi>Midas</hi> touch</l>
                  <l>Turne them to gold, or doth th'industrious Dutch</l>
                  <l>Through our owne sloth in this long time of peace,</l>
                  <l>In nauall strength grow out of our decrease?</l>
                  <l>If one, or all of these such ill produce,</l>
                  <l>Let London seeke redresse for such abuse,</l>
                  <l>And studdy to vphold her nauall fame,</l>
                  <l>From whence at first she did deriue her name,</l>
                  <l>That so each eye that enuies at her good,</l>
                  <l>May feare her nauies force on Thames great flood,</l>
                  <l>That king of riuers, whose<note n="*" place="margin">London<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Bridge.</note> rich-arched crowne,</l>
                  <l>Be girts his temples like a stately towne,</l>
                  <l>"Whom the pale<note n="*" place="margin">he Moone</note> Queene of waters, and of woods,</l>
                  <l>Doth most affect of all the fishfull floods,</l>
                  <l>And he againe, as if enamour'd on her</l>
                  <l>Oft at that time, when she doth take vpon her</l>
                  <l>Her full-fac'd beautie, flowing, swels with ioy</l>
                  <l>Aboue his bankes, and when as seeming coy,</l>
                  <l>And mounting in the East aloofe she keepes,</l>
                  <l>Following her with his waues, the shores he sweepes</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Goodwins</hi> sands with thousand wrackes enricht,</l>
                  <l>"As farre almost, as where those stakes are pitcht,</l>
                  <l>Where Thames too shallow running by the shore,</l>
                  <l>When the poore Brittons did his helpe implore,</l>
                  <l>Could not impeach the Romane hoast to passe,</l>
                  <l>Where then this kingdomes Empire yeelded was;</l>
                  <l>And where the stout <hi>Cassibiline</hi> gaue place</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Caesars</hi> force, betrayd by <hi>Mandubrace.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O noble Thames, who for thy quiet roade</l>
                  <l>Which to the wind-wrackt sayles yeelds safe abode,</l>
                  <l>When seas to seeke for safetie them compell;</l>
                  <l>All other floods not onely dost excell,</l>
                  <l>But for those ancient learned Bards of yore</l>
                  <l>And moderne wits, who bred vpon thy shore,</l>
                  <l>And fed with sacred fire, haue sung the praise</l>
                  <l>Of their great Maker in immortall layes,</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:177744:32"/>
                  <l>With voyces so diuine, that thou maist dare</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Tybur, Po,</hi> or <hi>Sein</hi> to make compare;</l>
                  <l>Still maist thou flourish, and still further flow</l>
                  <l>With thy sweet streame, to grace faire London so,</l>
                  <l>That future times to her may giue that honour,</l>
                  <l>Which former ages all bestow'd vpon her:</l>
                  <l>But carryed with thy winding streames delight</l>
                  <l>Beyond thy flow, London being out of sight,</l>
                  <l>We do forget what glorie she hath wonne</l>
                  <l>By the great deeds of many a natiue sonne:</l>
                  <l>Then let vs with thy ebbe fall downe againe,</l>
                  <l>And taking land at London there remaine,</l>
                  <l>Preparing aptest stile to sing the storie</l>
                  <l>Of her true noble armes and ancient glorie.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:177744:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> "London in sence a nauall Cittie is.</head>
               <p>OF king <hi>Luds</hi> reedifying London and leauing his name to the same, many hauing no better proofe then his picture, late erected on the frontispice of Ludgate, will condemne my Muse for not communicating in their opinion, to whom, though it should be granted, that such a king there might haue bene, yet may it bee doubted where hee did then finde Masons and workemen for such a building, which they say he then ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: <hi>Caesar,</hi> who was an eye witnesse of what he hath written, <hi>Strabo, Tacitus,</hi> and others, all liuing after that time, vnder which the Brittish historie placeth <hi>Lud,</hi> affirme a towne with the Brittans in their times to haue bene no other then a wood, as I before noted, in which they did raise rude cottages, fencing it about with a deepe ditch and a trench, they hauing no houses, vntill<note n="a" place="margin">Tacitus in the life A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricola.</note>
                  <hi>Agricola</hi> Liefetenant here vnder <hi>Domitian,</hi> did teach them to build Temples and places of publike assembly, much lesse could they then vse bricke or stone; and though <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> the mother of <hi>Constantine</hi> did, as<note n="b" place="margin">Simon. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel. and Hen. Hunting.</note> some thinke anno, <hi>306.</hi> build the walles of London; yet after that time <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius</hi> the yonger being Emperor, anno. <hi>434.</hi> I reade that the Romans taught the Brittons for their defence against the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursions of the Pictes, to build a wall of stone, without whose direction they had no knowledge of that kinde of building. The first man, that brought the Masons art of working of stone into this Ile (except that which the Romans had built) was<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn Stowe in his suruay.</note>
                  <hi>Bē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> Abbot of Wirrall, who was Master to the reuerent <hi>Bede</hi> anno <hi>680.</hi> and therefore leauing those deriuations of name
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177744:33"/> from <hi>Lud</hi> and the like, my Muse led by that great<note n="d" place="margin">Camden in Trinobanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> light of Antiquitie, deriues the name of London from her nauigation, as hauing euer bin a place of great shipping: for as saith mine author <hi>Lhongh</hi> in the Brittish tongue signifies as much as nauall or of ships, and the Brittish word <hi>dinas,</hi> which the Latins turne to <hi>Dinum,</hi> signifies a cittie, so that <hi>Londinum</hi> or London im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports as much as a cittie of ships. In a funerall Poem of <hi>Nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> an ancient Bard or Poet amongst the Brittons, it is called <hi>Lhongh-porh,</hi> that is a port of ships; many citties haue had the like Etimoligie of name, as<note n="e" place="margin">Strabo lib. <hi>8</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Naupactus</hi> a towne in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolia, <hi>Nauplia</hi> a towne in Argos, which were so called for the many ships that did frequent them. But from them and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cities, London may iustly challenge that nauall name, being of such ancient fame and renowne for shipping and merchants, as I before noted.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>"Vpon that fruitfull countries hilles, the key</l>
                  <l>That opens Englands ports —</l>
               </q>
               <p>My Muse viewing the wonted nauall forces of this cittie and as one hauing bene out at sea, in her returne at the Thames mouth takes viewe of Kent, in all ages accounted the key of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therefore the Norman after his conquest of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to keepe it the safer, appointed a Constable of Douer-Castle, and the same man Lord Warden of the <hi>5.</hi> Ports, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the cinque ports, according to the ancient custome of the Romans, who instituted a Praefect or Goruernour, called<note n="f" place="margin">Amianus Marcellinus.</note>
                  <hi>tractus maritimi comes.</hi> The Lord Warden of the cinque ports, is alwaies one of the noble Peeres of this kingdome, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to that honour for reputation of his faith and vertue, as now of late is that noble Gentleman the Lord <hi>Zouch,</hi> one of our Soueraignes most honourable priuie Councell: the names of the ports are these, <hi>Douer, Sandwich, Rumney, Hith</hi> and <hi>Hastings,</hi> the first foure being in Kent, the last in Sussex, all which do enioy many large priuiledges and immunities before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maritine townes.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:177744:34"/>That good Dukes house, which now the grene banke names.</q>
               <p>The kings pallace of Greenewich was first builded by <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcy</hi> Duke of Glocester in the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixth, which <hi>Henrie</hi> the seuenth did much augment, and finished that house in the top of the hill, which was begunne by the saide Duke, it was royalized by the birth of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight; but especially memorable, for that in the same the glorie of her sex, that royall Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was happily brought to light; Duke <hi>Humphry</hi> cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it Pleasance, but that name dyed with him, or not long after, it is now called after the name of the town Grenewich; that is the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eene banke. For the banke of a riuer is <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c</hi> in the Germane tongue) famous in times past, for the crueltie of the <hi>Danes</hi> against <hi>Ealphegus</hi> Archbishop of Canterburie whom they there did martyr with most exquisite torments, whose martyrdome is set downe, by an<note n="a" place="margin">Apud Cā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ex dit mari Merse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgij libro Clero. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> ancient writer of the same time.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Whom the pale Queene of waters and of woods</l>
                  <l>Doth most affect of all the fishfull floods.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This fiction of the ardent loue betwixt the Moone and the riuer of Thames is intelligible enou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to all, that know the affinitie betwixt her, the Ocean, and all moist bodies, whose influence is, as much (if not more powerfull) on this, as on any riuer of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, as may appeare by that admirable ebbing and flowing of the Thames, which from the Ocean flowes vp into the land lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle lesse then sixtie miles, and sometimes more. The cause is, as well attributed to the motion of the celestiall orbes, as to the Moone from East to West, the riuer continuing his course the same way. The cause of the many differences of the Thames ebs and floods, which on our coasts by forreine<note n="b" place="margin">Tacitus in the life of Agricola.</note> writers hath long since bene obserued as a note of wonder: I leaue as inscrutable, able to confound another <hi>Stagerite,</hi> of whom it is<note n="c" place="margin">Coelius Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dodogunus antiquarum lectionum lib. <hi>29</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> sayd, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into the Oceans strange and vniuersall motion in this kind,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177744:34"/> that he died of grief and vexation of not finding out that hiden secret. One note more of this famous riuer, is, that as it is more nauigable, so doth it communicate the commodities of nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion farther into the land, then any riuer of this kingdome. The streame from the spring, where it doth rise, which is in the plains of Coteswold by Tetburie in Glocestershire, vntill it fall into the Ocean, shooteth and windeth it selfe betweene the land one hundred and <hi>80.</hi> miles.</p>
               <q>"As farre almost as where those stakes are pitcht.</q>
               <p>That is, neare Otelands where the riuer at this day being scarse sixe foote deepe; <hi>Cassibiline</hi> and his Brittons, to impeach the passage of <hi>Caesar</hi> and his Romans, did pight sharpe stakes vpon the banke and in the bottome of the riuer, of which that place is at this day cald <hi>Coway stakes.</hi> The reuerent <hi>Bede</hi> describing them to be as big as a man thigh, sayes, that when he liued, they were there to be seene.</p>
               <div n="7" type="song">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:177744:35"/>
                  <head>CANTO VII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>Londons faire armes with honour wonne,</l>
                     <l>And grace to her by Princes donne.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis Queene of citties, Lady of this Ile,</l>
                     <l>So happy seated both for ayre and soyle,</l>
                     <l>Famous in name from all antiquitie</l>
                     <l>To keepe the same vnto posteritie:</l>
                     <l>Vpon her lap did nourse those sonnes of Fame,</l>
                     <l>Whose deeds do now nobilitate her name;</l>
                     <l>From her faire bosome sprang that royall stem,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Constantine the great.</note>Who, for the worlds imperiall Diadem</l>
                     <l>Did with his Brittons, famous then for armes,</l>
                     <l>Oppose <hi>Maxenius</hi> and his magicke charmes;</l>
                     <l>And in the East his standards did aduance,</l>
                     <l>Where proud <hi>Licinius</hi> fell beneath his lance,</l>
                     <l>And in Byzantium planted <hi>Caesars</hi> seate,</l>
                     <l>Where for his conquests he was stilde the Great;</l>
                     <l>There of that ancient citie he did frame</l>
                     <l>Another London, giuing it his name,</l>
                     <l>Which on the Thracian Bosphorus his strand,</l>
                     <l>As London vpon Thames alike doth stand,</l>
                     <l>Nor did he there blot out of memory</l>
                     <l>His natiue London here in Brittanny,</l>
                     <l>But did confirme to it that happy name</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of great <hi>Augusta,</hi> adding to the same</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:177744:35"/>
                     <l>The honor of his mint, with charge to ioyne</l>
                     <l>Great Londons name to <hi>Caesars</hi> in his coyne:</l>
                     <l>But we will here let passe those mighty men,</l>
                     <l>Those royall kings and Princes, that haue ben</l>
                     <l>Her foster children, neither will I sing</l>
                     <l>That<note n="*" place="margin">Mand the Empresse daughter to Henrie <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> daughter, wife, and mother of a king,</l>
                     <l>Though London borne, nor of those battailes tell,</l>
                     <l>In which she being victor did compell</l>
                     <l>Stout <hi>Steuen</hi> to stoope, and on the throne did set</l>
                     <l>Her royall sonne our first <hi>Plantagenet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But let vs looke within thy walls,<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Henrie.</hi> 2.</note> if any</l>
                     <l>Of thy graue Senate, among whom so many</l>
                     <l>Haue swayd thy sword of iustice, ought haue done,</l>
                     <l>Whose fame vnto thy name renowne hath wonne.</l>
                     <l>Their glorie like a flame in darkest night,</l>
                     <l>Which dims a tapers shine, obscures the light.</l>
                     <l>Of feigned honor, which to many yet</l>
                     <l>In this blind age, is like a Sun that's set</l>
                     <l>Mongst Enuies clouds, no pencill yet that lims</l>
                     <l>So like the life; no Muse that with sweet hyms</l>
                     <l>Out at the eare can steale the soule, doth sing</l>
                     <l>Of Londons fame, or vnto light doth bring</l>
                     <l>Ought worthy of thy selfe, although thy name</l>
                     <l>A subiect be, that fits the trumpe of Fame;</l>
                     <l>What famous Muse did euer yet rehearse</l>
                     <l>That noble act, though worthy golden verse,</l>
                     <l>And with the starres eternally to shine,</l>
                     <l>Done by that worthy Senator of thine,</l>
                     <l>Who when that Kentish rebell ready stood</l>
                     <l>With dagger drawne to shed yong<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Richard</hi> 2.</note>
                        <hi>Richards</hi> blood;</l>
                     <l>And none, who then about the king did stand,</l>
                     <l>In his defence durst lift a loyall hand,</l>
                     <l>Did with his dagger strike the monster dead,</l>
                     <l>And by one blow, by which his blood is shed,</l>
                     <l>Did saue from death, destruction and decay.</l>
                     <l>The king, the state, and all that breath'd that day,</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:177744:36"/>
                     <l>"For which the dagger of so braue a hand</l>
                     <l>On Londons crossed sheeld shall euer stand,</l>
                     <l>As the faire ensigne of that honor got,</l>
                     <l>By merit of the noblest deed, and not</l>
                     <l>Like that, which begd and bought through euery age</l>
                     <l>To vpstart gentile, giues a feigned badge,</l>
                     <l>Whose scutchions wanting colours of desert,</l>
                     <l>Are painted by the hand of bribed art,</l>
                     <l>Which truth, as things of scorne shall wash away,</l>
                     <l>And future time shall laugh at their decay;</l>
                     <l>When that braue bloody crosse vpon thy shield,</l>
                     <l>And that reuenger set in siluer field,</l>
                     <l>Shall stand for euer and to euery age,</l>
                     <l>Though tonglesse tell thy honors; for no rage</l>
                     <l>Of iron-toothed time shall them deuoure,</l>
                     <l>Nor cloud-browd enuy shall, though it do lower</l>
                     <l>Vpon the honor of thy <hi>Walworths</hi> name,</l>
                     <l>Be euer able to obscure the same:</l>
                     <l>O famous man, had Rome so happie ben,</l>
                     <l>To haue enioyd so braue a cittizen</l>
                     <l>Amongst her worthies, what would she haue done</l>
                     <l>To thy great act, such glory to haue won?</l>
                     <l>If vnto him, whose hand did hap to saue</l>
                     <l>The life of one meane cittizen, she gaue</l>
                     <l>For guerdon of his deed, a crowne, a speare,</l>
                     <l>And as a marke of honor chaines to weare:</l>
                     <l>What ornaments of triumph could haue ben</l>
                     <l>To meane for thee, or for those worthie men,</l>
                     <l>That after thee successiuely did sway</l>
                     <l>Our Londons sword of Iustice to this day:</l>
                     <l>"Shall <hi>Philpots</hi> actes, whose<note n="*" place="margin">Philpot Lane.</note> dwelling place and name</l>
                     <l>Our streets record, though men forget the same,</l>
                     <l>Be drown'd in <hi>Laethe</hi> or in silence sleepe,</l>
                     <l>Who like a <hi>Neptune</hi> did command the deepe,</l>
                     <l>And did, when greater men stood looking on,</l>
                     <l>From foes defend his natiue shoares alone;</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:177744:36"/>
                     <l>For when that<note n="*" place="margin">Mercer a Scottish pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</note> stout sea-rouer vncontrould,</l>
                     <l>Vsurper-like through his great powre did hold,</l>
                     <l>The scepter of our Northerne seas, and strooke</l>
                     <l>The shores with terror, when he cast his looke</l>
                     <l>Vpon the marine townes, whom oft by stealth</l>
                     <l>Through couert of the night despoyld of wealth,</l>
                     <l>In flames he offerd vp, and with rich pray,</l>
                     <l>As slaues did leade th'inhabitants away,</l>
                     <l>Who then but <hi>Philphots</hi> warlike ships vnknowne</l>
                     <l>To king or state, did stoutly set vpon</l>
                     <l>That strong sea-thiefe, whom sea-men all did shun,</l>
                     <l>As braying goates do from the Lyon run,</l>
                     <l>From whom the seas large Empire they did win,</l>
                     <l>And with rich prize did brauely bring him in,</l>
                     <l>"Nor may I here renowned <hi>Exton</hi> passe:</l>
                     <l>In whom the world, as in a perfect glasse,</l>
                     <l>May see the image of stout constancie</l>
                     <l>Against corruption and base trechery;</l>
                     <l>For when that wanton <hi>Richard</hi> shut his cares</l>
                     <l>Against the councell of his faithfull peeres,</l>
                     <l>"Whose fall, that head composd by magicke spell</l>
                     <l>Vnto the world, though tonglesse did foretell,</l>
                     <l>Who sucking poyson from the pleasing breath,</l>
                     <l>Of soothing Sycophants, did seeke the death</l>
                     <l>Of his deare vnckle, and did thinke t'employ</l>
                     <l>Our Londons loyall <hi>Exton</hi> to destroy</l>
                     <l>That royall Prince, he would not dip his hand</l>
                     <l>In guiltlesse blood, but did the king withstand,</l>
                     <l>And at that time the noble Duke did saue</l>
                     <l>With many peeres from their vntimely graue.</l>
                     <l>O faithfull constancie where art thou fled?</l>
                     <l>Iust heau'n with those great worthies that are dead,</l>
                     <l>Hath wrapt thee hence, where sithence thou hast ben,</l>
                     <l>Too little faith is left in liuing men:</l>
                     <l>Thus thou, our mother cittie still didst beare</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:177744:37"/>
                     <l>The fruite of golden glory, men, that were</l>
                     <l>Both for their faith, and valour more renownd,</l>
                     <l>Then for their wealth in which they did abound,</l>
                     <l>Who like true Senators in peace and warre,</l>
                     <l>Did sit vpon thy states tribunall chaire,</l>
                     <l>To Londons glory purchasing renowne,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Mars</hi> his sword, as well'as by the gowne;</l>
                     <l>For in that time, when England wofull stood,</l>
                     <l>Hackt full of wounds and dabled all in blood</l>
                     <l>Of those whose gored bosomes weeping bled</l>
                     <l>Drops of life blood for those, that could not shed</l>
                     <l>Teares for themselues, when ciuill hate did set</l>
                     <l>"The royall Roses of <hi>Plantaginet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So deepe in crimson gore, that few could learne</l>
                     <l>How from the red the white Rose to discerne;</l>
                     <l>Then did the Elders of thy state set forth</l>
                     <l>Their vertue to the world, whose onely worth</l>
                     <l>Eu'n in the iawes of ruine still did raise</l>
                     <l>Thee vp againe in those death-threatning dayes;</l>
                     <l>For when on <hi>Henrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> heau'n had so decreed</l>
                     <l>T'auenge his Grandsire <hi>Henries</hi> bloody deed,</l>
                     <l>That as a <hi>Richards</hi> blood did <hi>Henrie</hi> staine,</l>
                     <l>So by a <hi>Richard Henrie</hi> should be slaine,</l>
                     <l>Then did that giddie people in their rage,</l>
                     <l>March vnder stout rebellion, treasons badge</l>
                     <l>And led by that false<note n="*" place="margin">Iacke Cade</note>
                        <hi>Mortimer</hi> of Kent,</l>
                     <l>Who did vsurpe that name by Yorkes consent,</l>
                     <l>Like to a thunder in a tempest fell</l>
                     <l>Downe from the Kentish hils, and did compell</l>
                     <l>Their way into thy streets, where traytor-like</l>
                     <l>Their captaine on thy<note n="*" place="margin">Londons stone.</note> stone his sword did strike;</l>
                     <l>But thy bold elders, whose perswasiue words</l>
                     <l>Could not preuaile, betooke them to their swords,</l>
                     <l>And with hot fight enforced those to yeeld,</l>
                     <l>That had before bene victor of the field;</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:177744:37"/>
                     <l>And after in succeeding <hi>Edwards</hi> reigne,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Faulconbridge</hi> by fire would constraine</l>
                     <l>Thee ope thy gates, those Senators of thine,</l>
                     <l>Vndanted <hi>Basset,</hi> and bold <hi>Iosseline,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With many more, did through those hostile flames,</l>
                     <l>Which burnt their gates, rush out with loud exclaimes</l>
                     <l>Vpon their foes, who fainting in the fight,</l>
                     <l>Did turne their backes and gaue themselues to flight;</l>
                     <l>For which our kings, on many a cittie-sonne,</l>
                     <l>That armes and gentrie by the sword had wonne</l>
                     <l>Did lay their swords, and for their loyall faith,</l>
                     <l>"Conferr'd on some the honor of the Bath:</l>
                     <l>But many here perhaps with narrow eyes</l>
                     <l>Looking on Londons glory, may despise</l>
                     <l>These things, as toyes, and boasting their descent</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Ioue</hi> himselfe, will wish fames lookes were rent,</l>
                     <l>Rather then with their gentrie in the same,</l>
                     <l>True honour any cittie-borne should name;</l>
                     <l>For many now the name of London scorne,</l>
                     <l>Whose ancestors were London bred and borne,</l>
                     <l>But in their glorie vertue must haue part,</l>
                     <l>For though, that for a fathers good desert,</l>
                     <l>Honor be giuen, as imputed good</l>
                     <l>To all, that are of his descent and blood;</l>
                     <l>Yet with their blood it is not captiue bound</l>
                     <l>Vp in their veines, not else where to be found,</l>
                     <l>As orient pearles and pretious gems adorne</l>
                     <l>Beauties faire necke, so nobly to be borne</l>
                     <l>Giues to posteritie a glorious name,</l>
                     <l>Yet vertue was first authour of the same,</l>
                     <l>And Fame <hi>Ioues</hi> Herrald, who best knowes such things</l>
                     <l>From good desert, deriues the blood of kings,</l>
                     <l>And sayes, who vants of armes and wants good deeds</l>
                     <l>Vpon the sweet of borrowd glorie feeds,</l>
                     <l>As vpon others honey droanes do liue,</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:177744:38"/>
                     <l>The sword and gowne the brauest armes do giue.</l>
                     <l>That<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Edward</hi> 3.</note> Diamon-sparke of honour, scourge of France,</l>
                     <l>Fierce thunder-bolt of warre, beneath whose lance</l>
                     <l>In foure maine battailes fought in bloody field,</l>
                     <l>Fiue mightie kings subdude, did flie or yeeld,</l>
                     <l>Thought it no blemish to his kingly worth,</l>
                     <l>"As champion for his London to stand forth</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The great honour done to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by this king.</note>With his foure sonnes, when on his royall tent</l>
                     <l>To twise ten thousand eyes he did present</l>
                     <l>Our cities armes, in honour of whose name,</l>
                     <l>Gainst all the world a iousts he did proclaime,</l>
                     <l>And with his sonnes, who well knew how to wield</l>
                     <l>The weightie lance, did take th'appointed field,</l>
                     <l>Where in guilt armes beneath a goodly plume,</l>
                     <l>He bore the prize from all, that durst presume</l>
                     <l>To be appelants in the tilt for Fame</l>
                     <l>Gainst his bold challenge, in his Londons name;</l>
                     <l>Wel did he know, whose iudgment nought could wrōg,</l>
                     <l>To whom the right of honour did belong,</l>
                     <l>And at that time, as <hi>Phoebus,</hi> though each night</l>
                     <l>To all the starres he do impart his light,</l>
                     <l>Yet to the Moone his lustre chiefly lends,</l>
                     <l>So he, although to all deseruing friends</l>
                     <l>The sun-shine of his grace he did extend,</l>
                     <l>Yet did his greatest light of glorie lend</l>
                     <l>Vnto our London, pillor of his state,</l>
                     <l>His arme of strength, his shield gainst forreine hate:</l>
                     <l>In his triumphant dayes, foure royall kings</l>
                     <l>With that blacke Prince, whose fortunes on the wings.</l>
                     <l>Of victorie did ride, till in deaths field</l>
                     <l>Fate with his life did bid his fortune yeeld,</l>
                     <l>All at one time did our Piccards boord did grace,</l>
                     <l>Where plentie in triumph take her place,</l>
                     <l>On whom attending, bountie was so free,</l>
                     <l>That maiestie it selfe may witnesse be,</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:177744:38"/>
                     <l>How Honor harbourd was in her faire brest,</l>
                     <l>"Whose Maior Monarch like foure kings could feast,</l>
                     <l>But these her vading glories must giue place</l>
                     <l>To her diuiner gifts of heauenly grace,</l>
                     <l>Long since a safe <hi>Assylum</hi> she hath bene</l>
                     <l>Vnto poore persecuted Christian men,</l>
                     <l>And oft hath shaddowed them beneath her wings</l>
                     <l>From th'inquisition of blood-thirsting kings,</l>
                     <l>For which all good from heau'n on her hath flow'd,</l>
                     <l>As in th'ensuing Canto shall be show'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:177744:39"/>
               <head>Illustrations.
<q>
                     <l>"But did confirme to it that happy name</l>
                     <l>Of great <hi>Augusta</hi>—</l>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>MY Muse hauing briefly recorded our Londons scituation, antiquitie and deriuation of name, beginnes the hymne of her honour with the title of Augusta, being a<note n="a" place="margin">Augustus, quasi hominis natura am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plior cognomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus est octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius. Dio. li. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> name of great honor and dignitie, which was giuen as an happie or auspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious name to citties, of whose future happinesse there was great hope; some, as I noted before, haue thought, that London tooke this name of the Legion <hi>Augusta</hi> there soiourning. Howsoeuer <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, sonne of <hi>Hellen,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ughter to <hi>Coyle</hi> King of Brittane<note n="b" place="margin">Fitzstephēs libel. de situ &amp; nobilitate Londini pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by Iohn Stow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> borne in London to confirm the name to it, appointing his mint herein Londō, vpon whose coin is read<note n="c" place="margin">Camden in Trinobant.</note>
                  <hi>P Lon. S.</hi> that is, <hi>pecunia Londini signata,</hi> called the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seer of his treasurie, as it is in <hi>Notitiarum libro, praepositus Thesaurorum Augustensium in Brittannia.</hi> Here I wish to be noted, how Princes in times past haue honoured this cittie. <hi>Edward</hi> surnamed the Confessor for his faith and holinesse of life, stiled London, <hi>Caput regni &amp; Legum;</hi> which the Conqueror succeeding confirmed: the great Charter of England saith, <hi>Ciuitas London habeat omnes suas le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges antiquas,</hi> kng <hi>Iohn</hi> called it <hi>Regni firmata columna,</hi> king Richard the second stiled it <hi>Camera Regis,</hi> as here and there you may reade in the passages of my Poem; since which time, if there be not the like or more true desert of honour in this citie, let comparison of this later and now present state to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, decide it.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:177744:39"/>
                  <l>For which the dagger of so braue a hand,</l>
                  <l>On Londons crossed shield shall euer stand.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Though the originall of this cities honourable armes bee not vnknowne, scarce to any, that hath but lookt vpon London; yet since writers doe varie, touching the manner, take it briefly from<note n="d" place="margin">Abr. Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out of the Annals of Hen. Knigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton.</note>
                  <hi>Henrie Knightone,</hi> Cannon of Lecister, then liuing, thus. When <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> anno <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> the second, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of that commotion, raised chiefly vpon abuse, done to maides, in collecting that money called pole shillings, by some pole greates for all, that were vndergrowne, that is, that had haire growing on their priuie parts, backt by many thousand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, came to the king in Smithfield, where approching so neere vnto him, that he might touch him, and hauing in his hand a naked dagger with which boy-like playing, and tossing it from hand to hand, he presumptuously demanded not onely reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the abuse before spoken, but many things preiudiciall to the kings royall prerogatiue: the king, though then of age not fifteene yeares compleate, and hauing but few of his seruants or true subiects about him, yet by silence and delay seemed to deny the same, which the rebell perceiuing drew neare vnto him, and taking hold on his horses bridle, had there, as it is to bee doubted, slaine the king, his seruants and followers looking on, had not <hi>Iohn walworth</hi> Maior of London, preferring duty to his king and countrie before the safetie of his owne life thrust his dagger into the rebels throate; for which the king did after adde a dagger to the armes of London, in the right quarter of the shield, which as a true badge of honor all men may reuerence since by that one act, as <hi>Iacke Straw,</hi> next in reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the rebels to <hi>Wat Tiler</hi> at his death confessed, the king the nobilitie, the gentrie, and the citie of London (which should haue bene fiered in foure partes and lackt that night, before which <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> was slaine) were preserued from destruction: of this if you desire more, euery chronicle is copious.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:177744:40"/>
                  <l>Shall <hi>Philpots</hi> actes whose dwelling place and name</l>
                  <l>Our streets record—</l>
               </q>
               <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Philpot</hi> Maior of London anno <hi>2.</hi> of Richard the second, one of those, that for his vallour shewed in that action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the rebels before mentioned, was knighted by the king, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many other<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn Stowe his suruay</note> his worthy deeds as hauing often supplied his soueraigne, by lending him great somes of money, and hauing of his owne cost furnished <hi>Thomas</hi> of Wodstockes armie, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of eight thousand men with shippes, to passe them ouer into Brittannie, hauing likewise released the armour of one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of the said souldiers, pawned for victuals, did at his owne charge (our Coasts being then grieuously afflicted with that arch Pirate<note n="*" place="margin">Ralph. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n, in Rich. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Mercer</hi> a Scottish man) wage a thousand souldiers, bestowing them in his own ships, for to ouerthrow or take this Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; for which, the Lords of the councell did after checke him with the note of presumption, in setting forth a nauie of men without their authoritie, though the action did turne to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good of this kingdome, which may seeme to haue beene a patterne to <hi>George Talbot</hi> Earle of Shrewsburie, who anno <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, hauing raised a power against the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in the North, did put forth this question, whether his fact in leuying a power without commission, though it were against the rebels, might be brought within offence to the Lawes, to which, though answer was made, that it was iustifiable: yet he not trusting to the same, did sue the kings pardon, of whom hee might haue expected thankes. This Sir <hi>Iohn Philphot</hi> hath left his name to the lane, where he dwelled, of which and of much more land about it he was Lord when he liued.</p>
               <q>Nor may I here renowned <hi>Exton</hi> passe.</q>
               <p>This Sir <hi>Nicholas Exton</hi> was Maior of London anno <hi>10.</hi> of Richard the second, whose honorable act, toucht by my Muse, I thus explaine. When<note n="*" place="margin">Raph Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> in Rich. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Richard the second, incensed by his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177744:40"/> minnions, <hi>Robert Veere</hi> Earle of Oxenford, and <hi>Michael de la Pole</hi> Earle of Suffolke, did intend the death of his vnckle <hi>Thomas</hi> of Woodstocke Duke of Glocester with other Peeres, who then in Parliament did fauour the suite of the commons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the said Earle of Suffolke, &amp; to giue effect to this horrible fact, wickednesse in all ages wanting no ministers, Sir <hi>Nicholas Brember</hi> promising his assistance in the execution thereof, did deuise, that the Duke and other Peeres vnder pretence of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inuited vnto a supper at this Sir <hi>Nicholas Extons</hi> house, then Maior of London, should be there murdered. To ioyne in this action, the king did sollicite the Maior with large offers of his fauour, and that failing thundered forth the threatnings of his kingly displeasure; but this worthie Cittizen accounting that honour infamie, which should be attained by such vnlawfull means, and more fearing the offence of God &amp; a good conscience, then the displeasure of his king, not so much, as yeelding conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie to the fact, did by the reuealing the plot to the Duke, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer both him and many other noble men from death.</p>
               <q>"Whose fall that head composd by magicke spell.</q>
               <p>Such as haue their fall determined, are seene to decline by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, of which, this king may be an example, whose fall, after the death of his vnckles, whom he tooke to be his enemies, grewe fast vpon him, through the hate of his owne subiects: many sad predictions did goe before the wofull change of so royall a king to a wretched Captine, amongst whom, this spoken of by the Muse was thus: In that Parliament of this kings reigne, held at Westminster and cald the mercilesse Parliament there was an head made of waxe by art<note n="d" place="margin">Raph. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len. in Rich.</note> magicke, which at an howre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to speake vttered these words thrise, and then ceased; first: The head shall be cut off: secondly, The head shall be lifted vp aloft: and lastly, the feete shall be listed vp aboue the head. About this time were many ominous prodigies the great<note n="e" place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sing in Rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>341.</hi>
                  </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of those two Plannets <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> then happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, after which followed not onely the iniurious dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sing and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177744:41"/> lamentable murthering of this king, of which all the Princes of Europe spake shame, but with it the two bloody factions of those famous houses of Yorke and Lancaster, descended from <hi>Plantaginet,</hi> of whom in the next place.</p>
               <q>The royall Roses of Plantaginet.</q>
               <p>The surname of <hi>Plantaginet</hi> began in <hi>Henrie</hi> the second and ended in <hi>Margaret</hi> coūtesse of Salisburie, daughter to <hi>George Plantaginet,</hi> Duke of Clarence, who was beheaded anno <hi>33.</hi> of <hi>Henrie 8.</hi> but of the factions of Yorke and Lancaster hauing often spoken in my Poem, I briefly giue you their originall thus, <hi>Edward</hi> the third on his wife Queene <hi>Phillip</hi> begot seuen sons <hi>Edward</hi> the blacke Prince, <hi>William</hi> of Hatfield dying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out issue; <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of Clarence, <hi>Iohn</hi> of Gaunt Duke of Lancaster, <hi>Edmund</hi> of Langley Duke of Yorke, <hi>Thomas</hi> of Woodstocke Duke of Glocester, and <hi>William</hi> of Windsor, who dyed young: <hi>Edward</hi> the blacke Prince deceassing before his father, left <hi>Richard</hi> his sonne, who succeeding his grandfather in the kingdome, was by <hi>Henrie</hi> of Bullingbrook Duke of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster sonne to <hi>Iohn</hi> of Gaunt king <hi>Edwards</hi> fourth sonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft both of life and crowne, which from the issue of <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of Clarence King <hi>Edwards</hi> third sonne, was vsurped by the Lancastrian Kings, <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, fifth, and sixth of that name, vntill <hi>Kichard</hi> Duke of Yorke, claiming the crown anno <hi>39.</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixth did deriue his title from <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of Clarence third sonne of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, this <hi>Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> had issue onely a daughter called <hi>Phillip,</hi> who married to <hi>Edmund Mortimer</hi> Earle of March, had issue by him a son named <hi>Roger:</hi> to <hi>Roger</hi> no issue suruiued, excepting <hi>Anne,</hi> which <hi>Anne</hi> giuen in marriage to <hi>Richard</hi> Earle Cambridge sonne to <hi>Edmund</hi> of Langley, Duke of Yorke; King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourths sonne, was mother to this <hi>Rcihard</hi> Duke
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177744:41"/> of Yorke, who to obtaine the right of his tittle, or to make way for his sonnes, who after obtained the Crowne, lost his life in the battaile of Wakefield, so that Yorke descended from the third and fift sonne of <hi>Edward</hi> the third vnited, and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster from the fourth: The royall Roses were the two cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances of both the houses, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> Duke of Lancaster giuing for his badge the red Rose, and <hi>Edmund</hi> of <hi>Langley,</hi> Duke of Yorke for his badge the white Rose.</p>
               <q>Conserd on some the honour of the Bath.</q>
               <p>When <hi>Iacke Cade</hi> or <hi>Iohn Mend-all,</hi> titling himselfe <hi>Iohn Mortimer</hi> Cousin to the Duke of Yorke, that hee might feele the hearts of the people, before the Duke should publish his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the crowne, came to London with his rebels anno <hi>29.</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the <hi>6.</hi> where he stroke his sword vpon Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n stone say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now Mortimer is Lord of this cittie: the cittizens dayly burthened with the abuses of the rebels, vnder the leading of Captaine<note n="a" place="margin">Raph Holl. in Hen. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Matthew Goche,</hi> famous for his actes in the Frenchwarres, did valiantly set vpon the rebels, and driuing them ouer the bridge into Southwarke, though with the losse of the saide Captaine, <hi>Iohn Sutton</hi> Alderman, <hi>Robert Heisand</hi> and many other hardie cittizens, did so daunt them, that the kings pardon once proclaimed, they left their captaine and returned euery man to his owne home. <hi>Iacke Cade</hi> flying into Sussex was there slaine by <hi>Alexander Eden,</hi> an Esquire of Kent. Likewise when the rebell <hi>Thomas Neuill</hi> bastard to the Lord <hi>Faulconbridge</hi> assaulted by the Cittie anno <hi>10.</hi> of of Edward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. with a powre of <hi>17000</hi> men setting fire vnto the gates of the same, the citizens did not onely defend the places as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted, but issuing out, did through their valiancie, put the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to flight with great slaughter, for which <hi>12.</hi> Aldermen, the Recorder and diuers others citizens were knighted by the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177744:42"/> king in the field, two of which, as Sir <hi>Ralph Ioceline</hi> Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">Iohn Stowe in his suruay</note> and Sir <hi>Matthew Phillips</hi> Goldsmith, with Sir <hi>Thomas Cooke</hi> Draper, were made knights of the Bath, anno. <hi>5. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, which order, though as others, which now corrupted may seeme to smell, yet in times past was of great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and in high esteeme. These knights of the Bath, so called of certaine curious ceremonies of Bathing and watchings, were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly created at the baptizing, coronation, or mariage of Princes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>As champion for his London to stand forth,</l>
                  <l>And his foure sonnes —</l>
               </q>
               <p>This was king Edward the third, who triumphed in battaile o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fiue kings, as <hi>Phillip</hi> king of France, who lost the battailes of <hi>Cresseie, Charles</hi> king of Boheme, slaine in the same battaile, <hi>Ihon</hi> the French king successor to <hi>Phillip</hi> taken prisoner by the blacke Prince in the battaile of Poicters; <hi>Henrie</hi> the bastard king of Spaine ouerthrowne by the blacke Prince in the bloody battaile of Nauarete, and <hi>Dauid</hi> king of Scotland taken prisoner in that battaile fought by Durham. This victorious king anno regni <hi>33.</hi> did appoint a solemne Iousts to bee kept in Smithfield in the honour of London, the French and Scottish kings being then his prisoners, where hee with his foure sonnes <hi>Edward, Lionel, Iohn</hi> and <hi>Edmund,</hi> with nineteene other great Lords, held the field for the Maior and his three and twentie brethren; there then being but foure and twentie Wards of London, Farringdon Ward after anno. <hi>17.</hi> of Richard the second being of one, for the largenesse thereof diuided into two, and Bridge Ward anno. <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth beeing pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased of the Cittie.</p>
               <q>VVhose Maior Monarch-like foure kings could feast</q>
               <p>These foure kings <hi>Edward</hi> the third of England, <hi>Iohn</hi> of Fraunce, <hi>Dauid</hi> of Scotland, and the king of Cypres who
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177744:42"/> came into Englaad at the same time about some affaires with the king, were with <hi>Edward</hi> Prince of Wales and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great States feasted at one time by <hi>Henrie Picard</hi> Maior of London at his house, where hee kept his hall at the same time for all noble men, or other that were willing to play at the dice or hazzard, his Lady keeping her camber to the same purpose for all Ladies and Gentlewomen:</p>
               <div n="6" type="song">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:177744:43"/>
                  <head>CANTO. VI</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>London with light of Grace endewd,</l>
                     <l>Heau'ns blessings, her ingratitude.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>THe kings of Gods, Monarch of heau'n, and Lord</l>
                  <l>Of land and Seas, who by his onely word</l>
                  <l>Made Earth our grandams barren wombe to beare,</l>
                  <l>Hath chosen London for his Sion, where</l>
                  <l>The sonnes of men should with true praise adore</l>
                  <l>His sacred Deitie, who with that whore</l>
                  <l>Of Babylon themselues should not defile,</l>
                  <l>Whose witchcrafts our late fathers did beguile:</l>
                  <l>But keepe that truth and that true worship teach,</l>
                  <l>Which t'our forefathers that graue<note n="*" place="margin">Ioseph of Arimathea.</note> man did preach;</l>
                  <l>Who in his tombe did with blest hands enshrine,</l>
                  <l>The glorious body of the most Diuine</l>
                  <l>Vpon his graue, which Glaslenburie showes</l>
                  <l>"That holy thorne, this Ilands wonder growes,</l>
                  <l>To which, as if that reuerent place did giue</l>
                  <l>A power more then naturall to liue,</l>
                  <l>That sacred bush as th'incarnations badge,</l>
                  <l>White blossomes beares, when winter most doth rage,</l>
                  <l>And since that happy time hath London ben</l>
                  <l>The Nurse of pietie and pious men,</l>
                  <l>Who fearing neither death, nor raging ire</l>
                  <l>Of bloody Tyrants with their blood in fire,</l>
                  <l>Sealing the truth, and closing vp their breath,</l>
                  <l>Haue soar'd to heau'n vp on the wings of death,</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177744:43"/>
                  <l>And heau'n for this like shewres of raine hath shed</l>
                  <l>Alternate blessings on her happy head:</l>
                  <l>For in times past her state did not aspire</l>
                  <l>Vnto that greatnesse which we now do admire,</l>
                  <l>For through all ages as <hi>Apollos</hi> Bay</l>
                  <l>When Winters breath blowes Summers greene away,</l>
                  <l>Mongst leau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lesse trees a leafie top doth show,</l>
                  <l>So hath she flourisht and still great doth grow,</l>
                  <l>Through powrefull vertue of her lawes diuine,</l>
                  <l>When all het neighbouring cities do decline,</l>
                  <l>Whose wants with her aboundance she de doth feed</l>
                  <l>Yet of the same her selfe doth finde no need</l>
                  <l>As seas int'other brookes their waters pore,</l>
                  <l>Yet they themselues want nothing of their store.</l>
                  <l>Mongst Christian cities iustly maist thou claime</l>
                  <l>The glorie of an elder sisters name,</l>
                  <l>And mongst thy honors count it no meane thing,</l>
                  <l>"First to haue seene the worlds first<note n="*" place="margin">Lucius.</note> Christian king,</l>
                  <l>Whose soule with errors canker ouerspread,</l>
                  <l>When powre diuine had purg'd and it had fed.</l>
                  <l>Vpon th'Ambrosia of the heau'nly word,</l>
                  <l>He did cast out thy Pagan gods abhord</l>
                  <l>With their Arch-Flammins, and in thee did place</l>
                  <l>Holy <hi>Theanus,</hi> giuing him the grace</l>
                  <l>Of Prelates primacie, and not amisse,</l>
                  <l>Thou being then this Iles M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tropolis;</l>
                  <l>Twise seau'n succeeding prelates in the chaire,</l>
                  <l>The Miter did as Englands primates weare;</l>
                  <l>But when thy Pasto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and thy people both,</l>
                  <l>Through plentie pust with pride so much did loath</l>
                  <l>Celestiall Manna, that our angrie God</l>
                  <l>Scourging the Britons with an iron rod,</l>
                  <l>Did iustly cast them out, and in their place</l>
                  <l>The English Saxon did receiue to grace,</l>
                  <l>Then didst thou lose thy Ecclesiasticke right,</l>
                  <l>And as that Britton<note n="*" place="margin">Ambrose Merlin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie, that faith should faile and then reuieue, when the See of Londō should adorne Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie.</note> Bard, to whose foresight</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:177744:44"/>
                  <l>Things future were as present, had foretold.</l>
                  <l>Industrious <hi>Augustine,</hi> who did vnfold</l>
                  <l>The misteryes of heau'ns free mercie showne</l>
                  <l>To th'English first, though then to them vnknowne,</l>
                  <l>"Transferd thy Pall by helpe of kingly power,</l>
                  <l>From thy great Thames vnto the Kentish stowre,</l>
                  <l>Yet though he did iuiuriously translate</l>
                  <l>Thy honorarie dignitie of state</l>
                  <l>He left to thee, what now renownes thy name,</l>
                  <l>True zeale, the glorious badge of Christian fame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Gods blessings vpon this citie.</note>For which great Natures God and first Creator,</l>
                  <l>Mongst all the citties in this worlds Theater,</l>
                  <l>Hath thus long kept thee safe from dangers doubt,</l>
                  <l>When thou hast seene destruction round about,</l>
                  <l>Oft with sterne visage wrinkled full of frownes,</l>
                  <l>The aire hath rent and torne thy bordering townes,</l>
                  <l>Oft hast thou heard thy neighbours sad exclames,</l>
                  <l>Deuourd by <hi>Mulcibers</hi> remorslesse flames,</l>
                  <l>Beheld whole countries with their fruitfull land,</l>
                  <l>Swallow'd by seas, and turnd to fruitlesse sand,</l>
                  <l>Where hounds haue coursd the hare, seene fishes scud,</l>
                  <l>And ships to sayle, where sheepe haue chewd the cud,</l>
                  <l>Dearths daughter, famine eating vp the store</l>
                  <l>Of all the land hath swallowd rich and poore,</l>
                  <l>And hard vpon thy walles hath often bin</l>
                  <l>Yet neuer or but seldome enterd in:</l>
                  <l>Sterne <hi>Mars,</hi> whose rage no mortall may resist,</l>
                  <l>Who with the buffets of his brazen fist</l>
                  <l>Doth knocke downe states, and with one fingers push</l>
                  <l>Bowres, towres, and townes doth into peeces crush,</l>
                  <l>With blood &amp; spoyl thy neighbor France being wasted</l>
                  <l>Hath with his breath her fruitfull vineyards blasted,</l>
                  <l>And with his arme hath bruized the Belgians bones,</l>
                  <l>And made aire sigh with proud Iberias groanes;</l>
                  <l>When heau'ns haue shadowd thee with wings of loue,</l>
                  <l>As hens their brood from rau'nous birds aboue,</l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:177744:44"/>
                  <l>And if thy God, whom thou in euery age,</l>
                  <l>Hast too too oft by sinne prouokt to rage,</l>
                  <l>Doth punish thee, he frowning father-like,</l>
                  <l>Doth with that plague thy disobedience strike,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Iudaes</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Dauid.</note> Prophet, Prince, and sweet voyc't Poet,</l>
                  <l>Of all the three did choose, who well did know it</l>
                  <l>More happie and farre better to haue ben,</l>
                  <l>To fall into the hands of God then men.</l>
                  <l>But why, thus watered with the plenteous showres</l>
                  <l>Of heauenly raine, dost thou yeeld weeds for flowres?</l>
                  <l>Why dost thou say, that men shall neuer cease</l>
                  <l>About thy streets to sing the song of peace?</l>
                  <l>Where painted <hi>Iezabels</hi> in loose attire</l>
                  <l>With eyes of lust, and lookes that sparkle fire,</l>
                  <l>Kindling desier in euery wandring eye,</l>
                  <l>Steale out the heart of him that passeth by,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Ahabs</hi> sad oppression, and that wrong,<note place="margin">The common sinnes of this citie.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That grinds the poore to dust, growes great and strong:</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Abels</hi> blood to heau'n for vengeance calls,</l>
                  <l>And loathsome surfet reeles against thy walles,</l>
                  <l>The seruants of thy elders, through thy tribes,</l>
                  <l>With leprozie of false <hi>Gehezas</hi> bribes</l>
                  <l>Are taken in the hands, and loose the sence</l>
                  <l>Of feeling any great mans great offence,</l>
                  <l>Blasphemous mouthes with pestilence and death</l>
                  <l>Corrupt thy aire, in which they take their breath,</l>
                  <l>Whose too too common oaths are growne so great,</l>
                  <l>That out at thy wide gates they cannot get,</l>
                  <l>But sticking on thy posts and walls, do stand</l>
                  <l>As tokens of that plague that's still at hand.</l>
                  <l>Thy yong men are become extortioners,</l>
                  <l>Thy beardlesse boyes grow subtle vsurers,</l>
                  <l>Thy strong men saint, their strength doth vade like smoke</l>
                  <l>Thy women rule, and men do beare the yoake;</l>
                  <l>Who through thy streets their costly pride do show,</l>
                  <l>Like Sions daughters mince it to and fro,</l>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:177744:45"/>
                  <l>Whose earings, wimples, vailes, and crispingpins</l>
                  <l>Are triflles to their tires, the baudie gins</l>
                  <l>To trap the gazer, and the certaine hookes</l>
                  <l>To catch the thoughts and captiuate the the lookes:</l>
                  <l>At their false eyes, that bold-fac'd pander pride</l>
                  <l>To wanton lust the windowes open wide,</l>
                  <l>Exiling thence ill-mannerd modestie,</l>
                  <l>As one too bashfull for their companie:</l>
                  <l>Friendship and kindred shun the man that's poore,</l>
                  <l>Against blinde <hi>Homer</hi> each man shuts his doore:</l>
                  <l>Capon-cramd Foxes do deuoure by sleight</l>
                  <l>The childrens portions, and poore orphans right,</l>
                  <l>All friendly loue, except selfeloue, is dying,</l>
                  <l>Iustice is bought, and faith away is flying.</l>
                  <l>But vp deare London, vp, arise betimes</l>
                  <l>To crie lowd, lest thy lowd-crying crimes,</l>
                  <l>Preuenting thy repentance drownd in sloth,</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy head, do bring downe sodaine wroth:</l>
                  <l>To sucke sweete honey now at length begin</l>
                  <l>From that faire hearbe of Time, to turne from sin,</l>
                  <l>Whence thou too long in thy prosperitie,</l>
                  <l>Hast suckt the poyson of securitie:</l>
                  <l>So shalt thou prosper still, and neuer doubt,</l>
                  <l>Though seas of danger circle thee about,</l>
                  <l>The King of glorie shall exalt thy name,</l>
                  <l>Heau'n selfe shall be the trumpet of thy fame;</l>
                  <l>But now t'is time, since thus long we haue bin</l>
                  <l>About thy streets to see thy state within,</l>
                  <l>To view thy surface and behold without,</l>
                  <l>What walls of strength do bulwarke thee about.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:177744:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> That holy thorne, this Ilands wonder growes.</head>
               <p>ALL the honourable attributes worth, and glorie of this ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie before mentioned, do come short of this one, that through all ages, it hath bene the Nurse of pietie, good letters and religion, which <hi>Ioseph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> who buried the body of our Sauiour, sent hither by<note n="a" place="margin">Chronicon. Glascon.</note>
                  <hi>Phillip</hi> the Apostle here plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>Patrike</hi> the Apostle of Ireland, affirmes it in an Epistle of his, who lead a solitarie life thirtie yeares in the Abbey of Glas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenburie, where he saith, and the ancient monuments of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey confirme it, that he was buried: for which this place was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by our Elders,<note n="b" place="margin">In a charter of liberties made to the same Abbey by Hen. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Prima terra Dei, &amp; prima sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum terra in Anglia:</hi> Here, as I haue bene credibly informed by the inhabitants about that place, and as it is by diuers writers recorded, an Hathorn doth grow which blossometh euery Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas day, which may be thought none of the least of the wonders in this Iland.</p>
               <q>First to haue seene the worlds first Christian king.</q>
               <p>That England, and therefore London, may stand for prioritie of receiuing the Christian faith, with any kingdome or countrie of Europe, take these testimonies with that spoken of before: <hi>Claudia Rufina,</hi> of whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh in his last Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Timothie,</hi> conuerted to the Christian faith, was a Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, of whose nuptials with <hi>Rufus Peudens</hi> that acute<note n="c" place="margin">Martiall lib. <hi>4.</hi> ephi. <hi>13</hi>
                  </note> Poet thus begins an Epigram, <hi>Claudia Rufe meo nupsit peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Pudenti:</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dorithaeus</hi> Bishop of Tire, saith that <hi>Simon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177744:46"/> Zelotes</hi> came into Brittaine to teach the faith, and that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stobulus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. cap. <hi>16</hi>
                  </note> whom S <hi>Paul</hi> mentions in his epistle to the Romans, was a Bishop in Brittaine, likewise some<note n="e" place="margin">Niceph. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4</hi>
                  </note> whose authorities are reuerenced, do write that <hi>S. Peter</hi> came into this Iland, and that S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Theod. de curandis grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus lib. <hi>9.</hi> Sophronius Patriarch of Ierusalem.</note> came hither after his second imprisonment at Rome. Howsoeuer it is manifest, that <hi>Lucius</hi> king of the Brittōs (who as <hi>Nenius</hi> saith, was called <hi>Leuer Maur,</hi> that is of great fame for the faith, which began here in his time) was the first Christian Prince in the world, conuerted to the faith by<note n="g" place="margin">In some Faganus and Duuianus</note>
                  <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatius</hi> and Damianus, sent hither by <hi>Eleutherius</hi> Bishop of Rome, whose<note n="h" place="margin">By Stowe in his Annal.</note> letter to king <hi>Lucius</hi> is recorded by our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, so that if prioritie of Christianitie might take place, both our Souereigne might challenge that attribute of <hi>Christianis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simus,</hi> and his Ambassadours precedence in all assemblies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other in Europe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>"Transferd the Pal by helpe of kingly powre,</l>
                  <l>From thy great Thames —</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucius</hi> hauing receiued the Christian faith in place of three Arch-Flammins and <hi>28.</hi> Flammins, idolatrous sacrificers to the heathen goddes, did institute <hi>3.</hi> Archbishops and <hi>28.</hi> Bishops one Archbishop at London, the other at Yorke, and the third at Carleon, he founded a Church in Cornehill, dedicated to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and in a table there remaining, it is written, that he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the same Church to be an Archbishops Sie, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane of his kingdome, in which <hi>14.</hi> Bishops sate successiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whose names are set downe by<note n="i" place="margin">In his booke of Brittish Bishops as it is in Stowes Soruay.</note>
                  <hi>Iossaline</hi> of Furdes; But in the Heptarchie of the Saxons, who from their first entrance into this Ile, had liued Pagans <hi>150.</hi> yeares or thereabout,<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. West alias Flo. hist.</note>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> the monke being sent hither by <hi>Gregory</hi> the first for their conuersion an. <hi>596.</hi> remoued the Pal from London to Canterburie, vnder <hi>Ethelbert</hi> king of Kent, contrary to that which <hi>Gregory</hi> had commanded, for which cause that ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Bishop of London,<note n="l" place="margin">Camden. Trinobam.</note>
                  <hi>Gilbert</hi> of Folioth did aspire the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of England.</p>
               <div n="9" type="song">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:177744:46"/>
                  <head>CANTO. IX.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>Londons first walls, first vse of shot,</l>
                     <l>The English long bowes long forgot.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>THe<note n="*" place="margin">Agesilalis.</note> sonne of stout <hi>Archidamus,</hi> to one</l>
                  <l>That askt, why <hi>Sparta</hi> being famous growne,</l>
                  <l>Had no strong walles to shield it 'gainst the foe,</l>
                  <l>The cittizens in muster arm'd did show,</l>
                  <l>And said: behold the walles of our defence,</l>
                  <l>In whom we Spartans put our confidence;</l>
                  <l>Our London, like to Sparta, seemes to say,</l>
                  <l>She puts no trust in strength of burned clay,</l>
                  <l>The vertue of the cittizens in field,</l>
                  <l>Not sencelesse stones the cittie safe doth shield;</l>
                  <l>Which harbord was in royall <hi>Henries</hi> thought,</l>
                  <l>Who the French Tourwaine and stout Tourney taught,</l>
                  <l>With Bullen batterd by his cannon shot,</l>
                  <l>To know his English yoake, so long forgot,</l>
                  <l>For vnto <hi>Caesar</hi> viewing England well,</l>
                  <l>And saying, that in all it did excell,</l>
                  <l>Except in strength of walles, he did present</l>
                  <l>In little space, ere many houres were spent,</l>
                  <l>A royall hoast of force in field to fight</l>
                  <l>With the whole world in their deare countries right:</l>
                  <l>And vnto <hi>Caesar</hi> wondring at such powres,</l>
                  <l>Said, such as these are Englands walles and towres.</l>
                  <l>Yet Londons walls of yore were stronger farre,</l>
                  <l>Then now they be to beare the brunts of warre;</l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:177744:47"/>
                  <l>For when like floating <hi>Delos</hi> on the deepe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Description of the siege of London by by the Danes. an. <hi>1016.</hi>
                     </note>Cold Denmarkes winged woods the seas did sweepe</l>
                  <l>Towards our London, when their sodaine sight</l>
                  <l>Did put our fishfull Thames to fearfull flight,</l>
                  <l>Who carryed on the wings of his swift tide</l>
                  <l>Vnto his bankes, as he along did glide;</l>
                  <l>Did sound th'alarum of th'approching Dane,</l>
                  <l>And for reliefe to London came amaine;</l>
                  <l>Then, as vnnumbred Ants in sommer time,</l>
                  <l>When danger threatens them, by troopes do clime</l>
                  <l>Their little mount, and fortifie it strong</l>
                  <l>On euery side, to saue their egges from wrong;</l>
                  <l>Londons inhabitants ranne all to armes,</l>
                  <l>To shield their children, wiues, and friends from harms:</l>
                  <l>The earth did smoake beneath their mouing feete,</l>
                  <l>A horride noyse did ring through euery streete</l>
                  <l>Of clattering armes, some men with busie paines</l>
                  <l>Athwart the streets did draw the iron chaines;</l>
                  <l>Some kept the gates, each where our armed powres</l>
                  <l>Farre off appeard vpon thē walles and towres;</l>
                  <l>Whence they beheld their foes in braue aray,</l>
                  <l>As thicke as Bees from hiue in sommers day,</l>
                  <l>Descending from their ships to shore, and led</l>
                  <l>By bold <hi>Canutus,</hi> who with furie fed</l>
                  <l>"T'auenge the generall slaughter of that night</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Dane, did bring them on to fight:</l>
                  <l>Their ladders and their engins were applide,</l>
                  <l>And the stout foes did scale on euery side;</l>
                  <l>Then th'English and the Dane met man to man,</l>
                  <l>And on the walles a dreadfull fight began;</l>
                  <l>With loud exclaimes in slaughter, blood and dust,</l>
                  <l>They fiercely fought, sword against sword was thrust,</l>
                  <l>Shield batterd shield, face against face was set,</l>
                  <l>Earth seemd like heau'n to thunder as they met;</l>
                  <l>Death houering here and there on either side,</l>
                  <l>Found ghastly wounds gaping like windows wide</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:177744:47"/>
                  <l>To let him in, here from two bodyes slaine,</l>
                  <l>Th'one English borne, the other of some Dane;</l>
                  <l>Two streams of blood creeping apart did run,</l>
                  <l>As if in hate they did each other shun,</l>
                  <l>And would not then in death commixed be,</l>
                  <l>That in the life before could not agree;</l>
                  <l>The earth did blush with blood of bodies dead,</l>
                  <l>Aire gron'd with sighes of grudging soules that fled</l>
                  <l>Out at their wounds, the foes did fall apace,</l>
                  <l>Some scalded from aboue in wofull case,</l>
                  <l>Howling and yelling fled, some from the wall,</l>
                  <l>Pitcht headlong on their friends, vnlookt for fall,</l>
                  <l>Fortune with victory did London crowne,</l>
                  <l>And in her scale the Danes hard lot sunke downe;</l>
                  <l>Who from the walls repulst, yet many a day,</l>
                  <l>About the same strongly entrenched lay,</l>
                  <l>Till valiant <hi>Edmund</hi> with a heart of brasse,</l>
                  <l>And Iron sides, through warres dread paths did passe,</l>
                  <l>And rowzd them thence, giuing them such a blow,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Brentford</hi> with their blood did ouerflow;</l>
                  <l>But in this age if valiant hearts do fayle vs,</l>
                  <l>What walls although of brasse will ought auaile vs?</l>
                  <l>"Since that <hi>Promethean</hi> Monke by wicked wit,</l>
                  <l>If not from heau'n, yet from th'infernall pit,<note place="margin">First inuentiō of powder and shot.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That horrid thunder and swift lightning brought,</l>
                  <l>With which in iron pipes shut vp, he taught</l>
                  <l>The politike Venetian in distresse,</l>
                  <l>T'oppose their foes, that did their state oppresse;</l>
                  <l>From whence as if we meant to mocke the skies,<note place="margin">A Descriptiō of great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The world that brazen torment did deuise,</l>
                  <l>Which like a cloud including sulphurie stuffe,</l>
                  <l>Once toucht by fire with a violent puffe,</l>
                  <l>Spits out a lightning from his brazen chaps,</l>
                  <l>In rowling smoake and roaring thunderclaps;</l>
                  <l>And with it sends on wings of his strong breath,</l>
                  <l>A murdering bullet bearing certaine death</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:177744:48"/>
                  <l>To those it haps to hit, which as it flies,</l>
                  <l>Doth round, round rowle, roaring aboue in skies,</l>
                  <l>And like <hi>Ioues</hi> thunder, which it doth resemble,</l>
                  <l>Makes earth to quake, and those that heare it tremble;</l>
                  <l>O wretched man, since man it was did finde</l>
                  <l>This ruthlesse murderer of humane kinde;</l>
                  <l>Why did the soules inuention, which doth sit,</l>
                  <l>As the chiefe master in the mint of wit,</l>
                  <l>Worke without helpe of iudgement to foresee,</l>
                  <l>How fatall to the world, but most to thee,</l>
                  <l>O England it would proue, which at the first</l>
                  <l>Ioynd with that fierce debate, which out did burst</l>
                  <l>Like to a fire twixt Lancaster and Yorke,</l>
                  <l>The fall of thy great fame in France did worke,</l>
                  <l>"By which great Salisbury, the first of all</l>
                  <l>Our English Worthies, wofully did fall,</l>
                  <l>And felt those smarting wounds, while he did liue,</l>
                  <l>Which after vnto vs the Gun should giue:</l>
                  <l>For since that time, this torments dreadfull sound,</l>
                  <l>Hath put to scorne, and in deepe silence drownd,</l>
                  <l>The wonted terror of our English name,</l>
                  <l>Which our death-headed arrowes, wing'd with fame;</l>
                  <l>As they did flie from out our English bowes;</l>
                  <l>Haue whistled through the aire to all our foes;</l>
                  <l>"The Normans with their long bowes victors-like,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The first vse of the long bow.</note>At <hi>Battaile,</hi> where that battaile they did strike,</l>
                  <l>With Englands <hi>Harrold,</hi> for this kingdomes crowne,</l>
                  <l>Did teach vs first this lesson of renowne,</l>
                  <l>Where though the English and their valiant king,</l>
                  <l>As much as powre of man to passe could bring,</l>
                  <l>In fight perform'd, and offring vp their breath,</l>
                  <l>Did in the field not shrinke one foote from death:</l>
                  <l>Yet famous <hi>Harrold</hi> striken in the braine</l>
                  <l>With fatall shaft, and all his captaines slaine,</l>
                  <l>The foes through so much blood obtaind the fight,</l>
                  <l>That heau'n hath seldome seene so bloody sight,</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:177744:48"/>
                  <l>Which as that blazing starre before foretold,</l>
                  <l>So at this day with wonder we behold</l>
                  <l>"The earth there after euery little raine</l>
                  <l>Weepe drops of blood for her deare sonnes their slaine,</l>
                  <l>But when our English conquerd by the bow,</l>
                  <l>The perfect vse of it did after know,</l>
                  <l>As conquest did depend on Archerie,</l>
                  <l>They made themselues the heires of victorie;</l>
                  <l>How oft hath fruitfull France halfe dead with feare</l>
                  <l>Losing all courage, hung the head to heare</l>
                  <l>The flight of our swift fetherd arrowes, tell</l>
                  <l>The danger of their fall, before they fell?</l>
                  <l>How oft in field, as thunder-strooke lookt pale,</l>
                  <l>To see them comming like a storme of haile,</l>
                  <l>And heare her French aire sigh, as it did ake</l>
                  <l>With paine of wounds,<note place="margin">A complain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> on the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie.</note> which Englands shafts did make</l>
                  <l>(O famous armes of our great ancestors))</l>
                  <l>The onely strength and sinewes of their warres,</l>
                  <l>How are ye now neglected euery where,</l>
                  <l>By those whose parents once did hold you deare?</l>
                  <l>Where is your art, or whither is it gone,</l>
                  <l>As if with vs it neuer had bene knowne?</l>
                  <l>Alas how is it, that the wicked moath</l>
                  <l>Of idle ease, and ignominious sloath,</l>
                  <l>Eates vp the pinions of the gray-goose wings,</l>
                  <l>And frets in twaine our shaft far-shooting strings.</l>
                  <l>How is it that our London hath laid downe</l>
                  <l>This worthy practise, which was once the crowne</l>
                  <l>Of all her pastime, when her <hi>Robin Hood</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had wont each yeare, when May did clad the wood,</l>
                  <l>With lustie greene to leade his yong men out,</l>
                  <l>Whose braue demeanour, oft when they did shoot,</l>
                  <l>Inuited royall Princes from their courts,</l>
                  <l>Into the wilde woods to behold their sports?</l>
                  <l>Who thought it then a manly sight and trim,</l>
                  <l>To see a youth of cleane compacted lim.</l>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:177744:49"/>
                  <l>Who with a comely grace, in his left hand</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> description <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> one draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a bowe.</note>Holding his bow, did take his stedfast stand,</l>
                  <l>Setting his left leg somewhat foorth before,</l>
                  <l>His arrow with his right hand nocking sure,</l>
                  <l>Not stooping, nor yet standing streight vpright</l>
                  <l>Then with his left hand, little 'boue his sight,</l>
                  <l>Stretching his arme out, with an easie strength</l>
                  <l>To draw an arrow of a yard in length:</l>
                  <l>Which most praise worthie practise, since decayd</l>
                  <l>Londons<note n="*" place="margin">Opheley <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heriffe of London.</note> Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> once againe assayd</l>
                  <l>To set on foote, when many men did shew,</l>
                  <l>Both strength and skill to draw the strongest bow;</l>
                  <l>How in the aire, to thunder vollyes hot</l>
                  <l>From murdering mouthes of late inuented shot,</l>
                  <l>And how to manage strongest staues of Ash,</l>
                  <l>Which first the Switzer did inuent to dash</l>
                  <l>The drifts of their proud foes, and breake the force</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">First inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Pike.</note>And violent shocke of the steele-barbed horse,</l>
                  <l>Since when, some few, whom cōmon good hath taught</l>
                  <l>To know the good of exercise, haue sought</l>
                  <l>How to renew the same; but all in vaine,</l>
                  <l>Our greedy great men onely gape for gaine,</l>
                  <l>Our idle youth mispending time with shame,</l>
                  <l>Like boyes with beards, vse euery idle game,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The idlenesse and base <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ames of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge.</note>And dig our Londons field-paths round about,</l>
                  <l>Which children first for pins and points found out.</l>
                  <l>O base condition of our present state,</l>
                  <l>Where soules of children do inanimate</l>
                  <l>Bodies of men, no men, except in name,</l>
                  <l>Who like to painted pictures on a frame,</l>
                  <l>Somewhat resemble parents that haue ben,</l>
                  <l>But want that life which made their fathers men:</l>
                  <l>How like weake waters, lying calme and still,</l>
                  <l>Vnder the shadow, our long idle ill</l>
                  <l>Appeares in strangers eyes, who euery where</l>
                  <l>Laugh those to scorne, whom they before did feare:</l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:177744:49"/>
                  <l>(Deare England, thou great Queene of Ilands all,</l>
                  <l>Whom men the Nurse of armes might whilome call,</l>
                  <l>Thou valours whetstone, that hast often set</l>
                  <l>An edge on dullest nations, and hast whet</l>
                  <l>Cowards with courage, teaching them in field</l>
                  <l>To talke of conquest, that before did yeeld.</l>
                  <l>Why now art thou thy selfe so blunt and dull,</l>
                  <l>That others from thy head may seeme to pull</l>
                  <l>The crowne of <hi>Mars?</hi> the Belgians that haue ben</l>
                  <l>Thy pupils once, are now the famous men,</l>
                  <l>That great god <hi>Neptunes</hi> trident scepter wield,</l>
                  <l>Brauing Romes champion in the open field,</l>
                  <l>Vpon whose happie state though peace do smile;</l>
                  <l>Yet can it not their diligence beguile,</l>
                  <l>Base sloath th'industrious nation cannot wrong,</l>
                  <l>Laborious practise makes weake people strong:</l>
                  <l>Vp then for shame in vertue to stand still</l>
                  <l>And not goe one, hath bene esteemd for ill;</l>
                  <l>But to decline from good is worse then naught,</l>
                  <l>By light of ancient times let vs be taught</l>
                  <l>Old customes and good orders to renew,</l>
                  <l>Which our last Canto shall present to view.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:177744:50"/>
               <head>Illustrations.
<q>
                     <l>"Yet Londons walles of yore were stronger farre,</l>
                     <l>Then now they be —</l>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>MY Muse hauing taken view of the state of this noble cittie within, and now comming forth to behould her wals with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, findes them so decayed from what they haun bin, that, as to the people of a little towne, that had large gates, that Critticke once saide, Take heede (good people) that your towne runne not out at the gates: so may I say to the inhabitants of London, Take heede (O ye Cittizens) that your Cittie runne not ouer the walles; I know that though our Ancestors did not relie vpon the guard of our wals, yet they did so trust in thē, that they might be a defence against the sodaine incursions of a forraine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, or a domesticall rebellion: for they knew, that both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine foes, and the vagabond people of wicked commotions in our owne state, did alwaies, and now do with greedy desire affect the spoyle of this famous cittie.<note n="a" place="margin">Simon Du. Polidor. Ʋer. and onhers.</note>
                  <hi>Swaine</hi> King of Denmarke father of <hi>Canute</hi> with an huge host anno. <hi>994.</hi> besieged king <hi>Ethelred</hi> in London, but by the cittizens was repulsed with shame; <hi>Canute</hi> his sonne anno <hi>1016.</hi> inuioroned it with a mightie siege: of many more attempts, both by forraine enemies and rebellious insurrections at home made against it, our hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories are full, by which it appeares, that the wall at that time, was farre more defensible then now it is. A<note n="b" place="margin">Fitzsteph. apud Stow.</note> writer in the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the second, saith thus of it. The wall is high and great, well towred on the North side, with due distances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the towres: the Southside was also walled and towred; but the riuer of Thames, with ebbing and flowing through time hath subuerted them. The ditch intended for defence of the cittie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177744:50"/> anno. <hi>15.</hi> of king <hi>Iohn,</hi> was made two hundred foote broade; but now wasted with a consumption of incrochment, it is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen away, but as if greeued at the groning and sinking of the wall, vnder the heauie burthen of so many buildings, it is in many places runne quite out of sight; but of this I will say little, because little fruite will grow of seede sowne in such grownd; though it be a crime no lesse capitall then sacriledge to preferre priuate mens profite before the publike safetie: and therefore, though of euerie Cittie, that saying of the Psalmist bee true, yet is it verified of none so much as of London, except the Lord keepe the Cittie, the watchman watcheth in vaine.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>"T'auenge the generall slaughter of that night</l>
                  <l>Vppon the Danes —</l>
               </q>
               <p>This slaughter of the Danes happened anno <hi>34.</hi> of king <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> anno Dom. <hi>1012.</hi> at what time the English nation wasted with miserable spoyle through their frequent incursions from their first inuasions, which was an. <hi>791.</hi> were now not onely taxt with that insupportable tribute of <hi>(c)</hi> Daneguilt, but their wiues and daughters made prostitute to their beastly lust, they themselues became slaues: For the common people, were so oppressed by them, that they stiled them in euery house, where any of them lodged, Lord Dane, which since their expulsion, is in derision, turned to Lurdane. King <hi>Ethelred,</hi> to deliuer himselfe and his people from slauerie, instigated with hope of helpe, made by alliance through his marriage with <hi>Emma</hi> daughter to <hi>Richard</hi> the first, Duke of Normandie priuily sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited the English of euery house, where any Danes had their abode at a day prefixed, which was Saint <hi>Brices</hi> day, suddenly to put them to death, which was euery where at occasion best fitted, performed, in reuenge whereof, as the Muse telleth you, <hi>Canute</hi> king of Denmake and <hi>Swaine</hi> before him, inuading this kingdome, did besiege London, and were with losse and shame repulsed.</p>
               <q>Since that Promethean Monke by wicked wit.</q>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:177744:51"/>
               <p>As of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> who did steale fire from heauen to giue life to man, so of this Monke, the first deuiser of powder and shot, it may be said, that he did fetch the same frō hell by the labor of his working wit to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life frō man: it was brought to light, not long before the yeare <hi>1380</hi> in Germany, by<note n="a" place="margin">Polyd. de Iuent. rer. lib <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Cōstantine Anklit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> a Dutch Monke, some say a Franciscan Frier, who hauing powder of Brimstone and other sulphurous matter for Physicall vse in a pot couered with a tile did obserue, that a sparke of fire by chance falling into it did fire the powder, whose violence blew vp the tile, which he did after practise in little iron canes, and taught the vse of them to the Ʋenetians,<note n="b" place="margin">Fra. Guicc. hist. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> when they in their warres with the Genowayes vanquished by sea, were much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the losse of Chioze, they were after practised in Italy, then in France, and about sixe yeares after the first inuention seene in England. For when the French king,<note n="c" place="margin">Raph. Holl. in Rich. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the sixth intending the conquest of England anno. <hi>10.</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> the second had rigged <hi>1287.</hi> ships besides the sleete of Brittain, whose men of warre did boast to deuoure the whole nation, and to sacrifice the blood of the English to the soules of their Elders, amongst other their strange deuises for inuasion, there was made a woodden inclosure or wall in height twentie foote, in length or compasse three thousand paces, at the end of euery twelue paces stood a turret higher then the wall ten foote, able to containe ten men, this engine when they were landed in England, should haue inclosed their field being made with ioynts to take in peeces, but this frame with some quantitie of gun-powder and many guns was<note n="d" place="margin">By the Lord Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Callis</note> taken at Sea, and brought into England, which the French had no stomacke to follow. The first great Brasse pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cees were forged by the Frenchmen, which they vsed to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of all Italy in the reign of <hi>Henrie</hi> the seuenth, when <hi>Charls</hi> the eight descended to the conquest of Naples; the first great peeces cast in England which were but of iron, were made at Buckestead in Sussex, in the reigne of <hi>Henrie 8.</hi> anno <hi>1543.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>"By which great Salisburie the first of all.</q>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:177744:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Montacute</hi> Earle of Salisburie, a<note n="e" place="margin">Raph. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Hen. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> man both in pollicie and courage liker to the old Romans, then to men of his dayes, at the siege of Orleance anno <hi>7.</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixth, as he stood deuising in what place hee might best assault the towne, was slaine with the shot of a great peece from the wallet. This man was the first of our famous Captaines that did feele the effect of murthering shot.</p>
               <q>"The Normans with their long bowes victors-like.</q>
               <p>Some are of opinion, that the English from their originall haue beene skilfull archers, grounding the same vpon those Epithets and adiuncts of shooting, which we meete with in the<note n="f" place="margin">Dyonis. Fer.</note> Poets and passages of Historie, giuen to our ancestors the Sacans a renowned people of Asia; but others thinke that the Saxons did neglect, or not all vse the bowe, vntill after the Norman inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: for before that battaile fought betwixt Duke <hi>William</hi> and King <hi>Harrold</hi> by Battaile Abbey in Sussex, the Duke vsing words of encouragement to his Normans, told them that they were to fight with a people that knew not the vse of bowes: in that learned foster<note n="g" place="margin">Camden de Normanis</note> Father of Antiquitie describing this battaile, are these words: <hi>Primumque sagittarum grandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vndique emittunt, quod genus pugnae, vt Anglis nouum, ita omnino terrible erat, &amp;c.</hi> That is, first they that is the Normans, did shoot their arrowes as thicke as haile, which kinde of fight, as it was new and strange, so was it terrible to the English. Whensoeuer our nation began to vse this kinde of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie, it is manifest, that their knowledge and vse of it since the conquest in all their warres hath made them victorious and renowned through the world; the neglect of which in our time, if I should here lament, I should but reiterate the complaint of my Muse. It is said that since the inuention of the gun, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both vnprofitable &amp; vnseruiceable, of which if I may giue my opinion, I thinke it vnprofitable to a Captaine, though not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruiceable to a souldier, but leauing this to be decided by mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie men; I will onely note what seruice it hath done since shot
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177744:52"/> and powder were vsed: the triumphant victories of <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifth, with many ouerthrowes giuen to our enemies since that time by the onely vertue of our English bowes, though long after the inuention of shot I omit, and come nearer to our times, when it is certaine hand-guns were vsed. When king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight in person besieged Tourwaine, the armie of France intending the rescew thereof, the English<note n="a" place="margin">Edward Hall.</note> archers were placed by the side of an hedge neare a village called Bomie, who when the French battaile of horsemen passed by them to relieue the towne, did with their shot of arrowes so distresse and disorder them, that the fear and danger thereof did put them to flight without performing there intended feate. After this, neare Carleil by Sandy Sikes, as saith<note n="b" place="margin">In his school of shooting. lib. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> Master <hi>Roger Ascham,</hi> the whole nobilitie of Scotland (that nation being more resolute in armes then the French before spoken of) as both English and Scottish men, that were present at the battaile told him, were by the power of the English archers ouerthrowne and taken prisoners, and in the same booke he saith, that Sir <hi>W. Waldgraue,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Sommerset,</hi> did with fifteene archers at the Turne pike beside Hammes neare Callis, turne many French men to flight with their guns, to their great shame &amp; reproch. The opinion of<note n="c" place="margin">Sir Iohn Smithin his orders mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. p. <hi>145.</hi>
                  </note> one not meanely reputed in his time for matters militarie, is, that <hi>1500.</hi> archers well instructed, would beate <hi>3000,</hi> musketiers reduced into any formes of aduantage out of the field: His argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confirme the same are too copious to bee here insertd: and therefore I referre you to the author. One reason out of mine owne obseruation, I thus giue for archers: when generall mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters anno <hi>1588.</hi> were made through this kingdome against the Spanish inuasion, both in that royall armie, appointed for the guard of the person of that mirrour of Princes Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> vnder the conduct of the Lord <hi>Hundson,</hi> and in that field at Tilburie, where Sir <hi>Iohn Norrice</hi> the most famous souldier of his time, and many other Captaines of singuler reputation had command, archers, that were before, as it were with scorne by them neglected, were now, when a crowne and kingdome was to be decided by the sentence of the sword, approued and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:177744:52"/>
                  <l>The earth still after euery little raine</l>
                  <l>Weepe drops of blood.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In the plaine neare Hastings, where as I said before, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish and the Normans did ioyn in battaile, there is a place, which alwayes after raine lookes red, which<note n="d" place="margin">Gulielm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Neubrigen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> some haue attributed to the earth, as still sweating blood and crying to heauen for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, for so great an effusion of the same: but others and as I thinke, more truely attribute it, vnto the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the soyle, which his of red clay.</p>
               <div n="10" type="song">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177744:53"/>
                  <head>CANTO. X.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <l>Our Londons wonted practise shewd</l>
                     <l>Her marching watch both wishd renewd.</l>
                  </argument>
                  <l>HAd I the starres of heau'n, or all those leaues,</l>
                  <l>Of which the wind each yeare the woods bereaues</l>
                  <l>When stript of from their bows to ground they fal,</l>
                  <l>For counters to cast vp the summe of all</l>
                  <l>The martiall games and exercises done,</l>
                  <l>Since Londons state to flourish first begonne;</l>
                  <l>Yet would they not in my account auaile me,</l>
                  <l>Time would not serue, and memorie would faile me:</l>
                  <l>For Londons worthy sonnes in elder dayes,</l>
                  <l>By practise of good things to purchase praise,</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Mars</hi> his game, not <hi>Ʋenus</hi> sports their play,</l>
                  <l>In vacant howres to passe the time away:</l>
                  <l>Some like those Romans, who in sport did make</l>
                  <l>A mortall warre vpon that mightie lake</l>
                  <l>Before great <hi>Caesar,</hi> on our Thames would fight</l>
                  <l>Their nauall battailes, to the great delight</l>
                  <l>Of all spectators: some againe in field</l>
                  <l>Would practise feates of armes with launce and shield</l>
                  <l>"Who Barons at that time haue stiled ben,</l>
                  <l>Such was their glorie, such their practise then:</l>
                  <l>And from our <hi>Steuen</hi> to our last <hi>Henries</hi> dayes,</l>
                  <l>What mightie musters and what braue assayes</l>
                  <l>Of martiall shewes, in vse to keepe our armes</l>
                  <l>Hast thou (O London) made against all harmes?</l>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:177744:53"/>
                  <l>But thou wilt say, that then thy sonnes t'vphold</l>
                  <l>Such customes, freely would impart their gold,</l>
                  <l>But in this baser age, it is not so,</l>
                  <l>For in best actions now the best are sloe:</l>
                  <l>Though this, too true alas, do helplesse keepe</l>
                  <l>Such actions downe, yet from in glorious sleepe,</l>
                  <l>From out that strumpets sloaths inglorious bed,</l>
                  <l>Amongst thy sonnes lift vp the yong mans head,</l>
                  <l>And councell all the grauer to extend</l>
                  <l>Abounteous hand to euery worthy end,</l>
                  <l>At which all martiall exercise doth aime,</l>
                  <l>Gold is but drosse to the states publike fame,</l>
                  <l>And that we may in calme of peace prepare</l>
                  <l>Defensiue armes, against the stormes of warre:</l>
                  <l>And yet giue life to loue twixt friend and friend</l>
                  <l>Amongst our selues at home, the onely end,</l>
                  <l>For which such actions there beginnings haue,</l>
                  <l>The ghosts of our dead fathers from their graue,</l>
                  <l>By their late actions seeme t'intreate thy state,</l>
                  <l>That once againe they seeke to imitate</l>
                  <l>Their ancestors, in kindling those faire lights,<note place="margin">The vigils of S. Peter and Iohn Baptist.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which did illustrate those two famous nights,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Mars</hi> did seeme in triumph downe descending,</l>
                  <l>To stoope from heau'n vpon thee, and commending</l>
                  <l>Thy then triumphant March and martiall sport,</l>
                  <l>Deckt in his richest coate of steele,<note place="margin">A description of Midsom. mer watch.</note> did court</l>
                  <l>Peace in thy streets, conducting through the same</l>
                  <l>A warlike troope, that by that yearely game,</l>
                  <l>The noyse of armes made common to thy eares,</l>
                  <l>Might at no time disturbe thee with vaine feares;</l>
                  <l>When drums and trumpets sounds, which do delight</l>
                  <l>A chearefull heart, waking the drowzie night,</l>
                  <l>Did fright the wandring Moone, who from her spheare</l>
                  <l>Beholding earth beneath lookt pale with feare,</l>
                  <l>To see the aire appearing all on flame,</l>
                  <l>Kindled by thy bon-fires, and from the same</l>
                  <l>A thousand sparkes disperst throughout the skie,</l>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:177744:54"/>
                  <l>Which like to wandring starres about did flie;</l>
                  <l>Whose holesome heate purging the aire, consumes</l>
                  <l>The earthes vnholesome vapors, fogges, and fumes;</l>
                  <l>The wakefull shepheard by his flocke in field,</l>
                  <l>With wonder at that time farre of beheld,</l>
                  <l>The wanton shine of thy triumphant fiers,</l>
                  <l>Playing vpon the tops of thy tall spiers</l>
                  <l>Thy goodly buildings, that till then did hide</l>
                  <l>Their rich aray; opend their windowes wide,</l>
                  <l>"Where kings great peeres and many a noble dame,</l>
                  <l>Whose bright pearle-glittering robes did mock <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
                     </hi> flame</l>
                  <l>Of the nights burning lights, did sit to see</l>
                  <l>How euery Senator in his degree,</l>
                  <l>Adornd with shining gold and purple weeds,</l>
                  <l>And stately mounted on rich-trapped steeds,</l>
                  <l>Their guard attending through the streets did ride</l>
                  <l>Before their foot-bands, grac'd with glittering pride</l>
                  <l>Of rich guilt armes, whose glory did present</l>
                  <l>A sunshine to the eye, as if it ment</l>
                  <l>Amongst the cresset lights shot vp on hie,</l>
                  <l>To chase darke night for euer from the skie:</l>
                  <l>While in the streets the Stickelers to and fro,</l>
                  <l>To keepe Decorum still did come and go;</l>
                  <l>Where tables set were plentifully spread,</l>
                  <l>And at each doore neighbor with neighbor fed,</l>
                  <l>Where modest mirth attendant at the feast</l>
                  <l>With plentie gaue content to euery guest,</l>
                  <l>Where true goodwill crownd cups with fruitfull wine,</l>
                  <l>And neighbors in true loue did fast combine,</l>
                  <l>Where the lawes pickepurse, strife twixt friend &amp; friend</l>
                  <l>By reconcilement happily tooke end:</l>
                  <l>A happy time, when men knew how to vse</l>
                  <l>The gifts of happy peace, yet not abuse</l>
                  <l>Their quiet rest with rust of ease, so farre</l>
                  <l>As to forget all discipline of warre,</l>
                  <l>VVho oft hath heard wars thunder, seldome feares it,</l>
                  <l>VVhen it affrights his heart, that seldome heares it;</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:177744:54"/>
                  <l>For of those troopes, how many a mothers sonne,</l>
                  <l>VVhose cares of late could scarse abide the gun,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ind vp to hand it, now begin to know</l>
                  <l>The postures of the peece, which they did show</l>
                  <l>To many thousand eyes vpon that day,</l>
                  <l>"when London twise ten ensignes did display,<note place="margin">The muster on the <hi>8.</hi> of August.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beneath whose colours in her streets dispread,</l>
                  <l>And by the conduct of her owne sonnes led,</l>
                  <l>Those foot-bāds which twise thirteen<note n="*" place="margin">Wards.</note> tribes did yeeld</l>
                  <l>Deckt in bright armes did march into the field,</l>
                  <l>Where either side the other did oppose,</l>
                  <l>Troope charging troope, like true friends turned foes,</l>
                  <l>Wanting but order in that feigned sight,</l>
                  <l>Through want of space to do the war-god right:</l>
                  <l>For many thousand old and yong did range</l>
                  <l>The field from troope to troope, and wich is strange,</l>
                  <l>Thousands of our Viragoes stoutley stood</l>
                  <l>Amidst the rankes, as if through wounds and blood</l>
                  <l>In the plaine field, they had conspired then</l>
                  <l>Brauely to win the breeches from the men;</l>
                  <l>When many scard spectators fast did flie,</l>
                  <l>Who falling each on others neckes did lie.</l>
                  <l>Like dying people, groueling on the ground,</l>
                  <l>As if the shot had giuen them deaths wound;</l>
                  <l>While the strong pikes shaking with eagar ire,</l>
                  <l>For that they could not come to their desier,</l>
                  <l>Did threaten them farre of, and wings of shot,</l>
                  <l>Drawne out on either side did play so hot.</l>
                  <l>That men did loose themselues, groping for light</l>
                  <l>In clouds of smoake, as in the midst of night,</l>
                  <l>VVhose thunder Eastward through the aire mad roome</l>
                  <l>To eares of men, as farre as <hi>Harrolds</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Waltham Abbey where Harrold was interd.</note> tombe.</l>
                  <l>And when<note n="*" place="margin">The late muster the <hi>27.</hi> of Sept.</note> that Diamond sparke of royaltie,</l>
                  <l>That bud of hope, Prince of great Brittannie,</l>
                  <l>Like the yong Macedonian Monarch mounted</l>
                  <l>On his <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> from farre recounted</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:177744:55"/>
                  <l>The ensignes of each troope, before his eyes</l>
                  <l>The souldiers steele-topt pikes aduanc'd did rise</l>
                  <l>Like to a corne field wauing vp and downe,</l>
                  <l>And plumes of various colours, which did crowne</l>
                  <l>The souldiers heads beneath the pikes, did show</l>
                  <l>Like colourd flowers, which in the corne do grow,</l>
                  <l>The splendor of guilt armes refulgent light,</l>
                  <l>Danc't in the Sun before his royall sight,</l>
                  <l>As if their glittering gaue a shine more cleare,</l>
                  <l>And the red streaming crosses did appeare</l>
                  <l>Through the darke smoke of gun-shot thundring loud,</l>
                  <l>Like bloody Comets through a sable clowd:</l>
                  <l>But when <hi>Mars</hi>-like in field approching nigh</l>
                  <l>With martiall staffe vpon his Princely thigh,</l>
                  <l>Attended with a noble troope he came</l>
                  <l>Vnto the<note n="*" place="margin">Sir Thomas Hayes then Lord Maior.</note> Consuls tent, the lowd exclame</l>
                  <l>And cheareful shouts, which souldiers throtes did yeild</l>
                  <l>For ioy to see their Soueraigns sonne in field:</l>
                  <l>With louder thunder of thicke volleys giuen,</l>
                  <l>Did eccho his true welcome vp to heauen:</l>
                  <l>Before his sight, as euery seuerall band</l>
                  <l>Did march fast by the tent where he did stand,</l>
                  <l>The Captaines shining in rich gold, did show</l>
                  <l>Compar'd to'th souldiers, as the planets do</l>
                  <l>To lesser starres, the men in muster tooke,</l>
                  <l>For limbes composture and for manly looke,</l>
                  <l>For furniture, for armes and rich aray,</l>
                  <l>From other countries bore the praise away:</l>
                  <l>For what sterne eye of enuie, that beheld</l>
                  <l>Their martiall order at that time in field,</l>
                  <l>If equall truth might guide it, could in them,</l>
                  <l>Ought but the want of discipline condemne;</l>
                  <l>To which defect, since time, true ingenie</l>
                  <l>And practise yeeld the onely remedie:</l>
                  <l>O that god <hi>Mars</hi> more oft might sing his dittie,</l>
                  <l>In the soft eares of this our peacefull cittie,</l>
                  <l>And that the greedy gripe, that grasps his purse</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:177744:55"/>
                  <l>Fast in his fist, and grudges to disburse</l>
                  <l>His coyne to such good vse, would learne to know</l>
                  <l>That<note n="*" place="margin">Nil Spartā perdat nisi ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pecunia facta.</note> Oracle, which in times past did show,</l>
                  <l>That nothing could the Spartan state disioyne,</l>
                  <l>Except they made too much account of coyne;</l>
                  <l>And that our eldest sonnes of idle ease,</l>
                  <l>Whom nothing but the Taylors cut can please,</l>
                  <l>Would turne superfluous rags of wretched pride,</l>
                  <l>To plates of steele, lay oftentimes aside</l>
                  <l>Their slender switches for strong staues of Ash,</l>
                  <l>And change perfumes for sulphurie powders flash:</l>
                  <l>But vnto such I wish this good in vaine,</l>
                  <l>As I began, so must <hi>I</hi> end againe,</l>
                  <l>With Londons <hi>Mars</hi>-adornd Artillerie,</l>
                  <l>Her onely Nurse of armes yong <hi>Infantrie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bellonas</hi> spring where streames of knowledge floe,</l>
                  <l>Garden of <hi>Mars</hi> where plants of valour grow,</l>
                  <l>(Thrise worthy spirits) euer may you liue,</l>
                  <l>In fames faire booke, whose industrie doth giue,</l>
                  <l>Life to the loue of armes, who both with paine</l>
                  <l>And large expence, the schoole of <hi>Mars</hi> maintaine,</l>
                  <l>And since the fier of your forward harts</l>
                  <l>To all good actions both in armes and arts,</l>
                  <l>Warmes the cold hopes of London, to renew</l>
                  <l>Her ancient orders, chiefly vnto you</l>
                  <l>I by this pen-man do commend this storie,</l>
                  <l>As the true mirrour of our Londons glorie.</l>
                  <l>This said, the helme-deckt goddesse tooke her rise</l>
                  <l>Vpon her speare, and vanisht from our eyes,</l>
                  <l>Leauing the souldier and my selfe agast;</l>
                  <l>For he, who selfe-loue-swolne sought to blast</l>
                  <l>Our Londons fame, with enuious breath before,</l>
                  <l>Did euer since her noble name adore;</l>
                  <l>And by <hi>Minerua,</hi> as I was foretaught,</l>
                  <l>Lest her swift vision flying from my thought,</l>
                  <l>I should at last haue lost what I did thinke,</l>
                  <l>I thus did limme the Visions wings with inke.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:177744:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Illustrations.</hi> "Who Barrons at that time haue stiled bene.</head>
               <p>THe youth of this cittie in times past despising such effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate games as we now vse, which rather induce both body and minde to vice then to vertue, did<note n="a" place="margin">Fitz. Step. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e situ &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ltate Lond.</note> euery Friday in Lent practise feates of armes on horsebacke with disarmed lances and shields, and did also sight battailes on the water, thereby shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, how seruiceable they would be in martiall affaires; this was their practise in the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the second, many of them being called Barons, for after anno <hi>37.</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, I reade<note n="b" place="margin">Out of Ra. Holl. in Hen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that certaine of the court comming with a humour of contempt and scorne to behold their exercise, &amp; giuing reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full words to those Londoners, which were there called Barons, did suffer for their derision such stripes and wounds, that the king caused the cittizens to pay <hi>1000.</hi> markes for the healing.</p>
               <q>"Which did illustrate those two famous nights.</q>
               <p>Meaning the vigels of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> when that famous marching watch consisting of <hi>2000.</hi> besides the standing watches, were maintained in this cittie. It conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> vntill the reigne an. <hi>31</hi> of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, in which yeare it was laide downe by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence frō the king, for that the cittte had then bin charged with the leauie of a muster of fifteene thousand men, neither was it reuiued againe, vntill anno <hi>2.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth, by Sir <hi>Iohn Gresham</hi> then Lord Maior, since whose time the like watch in London hath not bene seene; I will not here dispute the conueniencie thereof, onely note the words of a certaine book
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177744:56"/> dedicatdd by a<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn Moūtgomer.</note> cittizen anno <hi>1585.</hi> to Sir <hi>Thomas Pulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> then Lord Maior and the Aldermen, the words are these, Artificers of diuers sorts were therby well set to worke, none but rich men charged, poore men releeued, old souldiers, wherein the safetie and defence of euery commonwealth consisteth, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, armour annd weapons through this occasion ready prepared whereas by intermission armorours want worke, souldiers out of practise, weapons ouergrowne with rust, few or none good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prouided, &amp;c. and so goes on with an exhortation to reuiue tht same: but as this, so the like good orders are vanisht and the fruite of sloth and couetousnesse growne vp, though some haue sought to restore the customes of our countrie, amongst whom I may not forget the good endeuour of that worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, Master <hi>Hugh Ophley</hi> Sherriffe of London, who did deuise the martiall shew of Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> onely to giue life to decayed Archerie the good endeuour of whom and of all those that now or hereafter shall immitate the like attempt, cannot want a praise-worthie remembrance with posteritie.</p>
               <q>VVhere kings, great Peeres, and many noble dame.</q>
               <p>King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight approuing this marching watch, as an auncient commendable custome of this cittie, lest it should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay through neglect or couetousnesse, in the first yeare of his reigne, came priuately disguised in one of his guards coates into Cheape on Midsommer euen, and seeing the same at that time performed to his content to countenance it, and make it more glorious by the presence of his person,<note n="d" place="margin">Raph. Hol. in Hen. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> came after on <hi>S. Peters</hi> Euen with Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> attended by a noble traine, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in royall state to the Kings head in Cheap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, there to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the same, and after anno. <hi>15.</hi> of his reigne <hi>Christerne</hi> king of Denmarke with his Queene being then in England, was conducted through the cittie to the kings head in Cheape, there to see the same.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:177744:57"/>When London twise ten ensignes did dispreade</q>
               <p>Both the late Muster of Wednesday, the <hi>27.</hi> of September and that before, on Tewsday, the eight of August anno <hi>1615.</hi> my Muse hath briefly noted, whose souldiers for their armes and furniture, both for seruice and shew, were well and rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, imitating the old Romans, in their garnish of feathers, which, as it is a sight<note n="e" place="margin">Nich. Mac. in his art of warre. lib. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> braue and terrible to the enemie, so is it goodly and delightfull to friends: In their demeanour I noted these two defects, ignorance of order, and neglect of their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines command, the knowledge of the first cannot bee had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out time and practise, nor respect of the last (except in the more ingenuous man) without more authoritie to inforce it: so that as<note n="f" place="margin">Fran. Guic. hist. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour being with king <hi>Henrie 8.</hi> at the siege of Tourwaine (where wearing <hi>S. Georges</hi> crosse, hee receiued <hi>salaire</hi> for seruice as the king of Englands souldier) gaue his iudgement vpon triall, that in matters of warre the English were then more resolute, then well aduised: and lesse sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and polliticke, then well disciplined and trained, so may it be here said of the late Muster, with which I conclude, that they were more rash and turbulent, then discreet and wel aduised, &amp; lesse instructed &amp; trained then will furnished and appointed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>